<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The raptures of a flaming spirit Being a directory, wherein methodically is contained the several parts of prayer. With select expressions for the performance of the duty. As the author useth to express himself before and after his sermons. By Nico. Pearson. &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Pearson, Nicolas, fl. 1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 156 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1010A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217486</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829149</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33585</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53902)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33585)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1974:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The raptures of a flaming spirit Being a directory, wherein methodically is contained the several parts of prayer. With select expressions for the performance of the duty. As the author useth to express himself before and after his sermons. By Nico. Pearson. &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Pearson, Nicolas, fl. 1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[42], 262 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. James for the author, and are to be sold by Robert Clavel and Richard Jones, at the Peacock in St. Paul's Churchyard, and the White Horse in Little Britain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"On the author and his elaborate work" on c5 is signed: G.H.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Maxims --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Aphorisms and apothegms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RAPTURES OF A Flaming Spirit.</p>
            <p>BEING <hi>A Directory,</hi> Wherein Methodically is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſeveral Parts of PRAYER.</p>
            <p>With Select Expreſſions for the Performance of the <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the Author uſeth to Expreſs himſelf before and after his <hi>SERMONS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>NICO. PEARSON.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>HOS. 14. 2.</bibl> 
               <hi>Take with you words, and turn to the LORD; ſay unto him,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. James</hi> for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>Robert Clavel</hi> and <hi>Richard Jones,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Churchyard, and the <hi>White Horſe</hi> in <hi>Little Britain.</hi> 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE OR INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>IT was uncharitably, ungratefully, and indeed enviouſly ſaid of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab, David</hi>'s Eldeſt Brother, when he ſaw <hi>David</hi> ſo vigorous and zealous in the <hi>Lords Work;</hi> That he came from home, to the Camp, in <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>Naughtineſs of heart,</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt himſelf, leaving the Sheep under his charge, expoſed to danger: <hi>Eliab</hi> not knowing that the thing was of
<pb facs="tcp:33585:6"/>
               <hi>God,</hi> and not conſidering he was ſent by his <hi>Father;</hi> and not <hi>Vacuis Manibus,</hi> but brought a <hi>Preſent</hi> to their <hi>Captain</hi> and <hi>Suſtenance</hi> for <hi>himſelf</hi> and <hi>brethren.</hi> I am ſure to meet with ſuch miſinterpretation and ſuſpect from my <hi>Anti-ingenious Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> of whom I ſay as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Copper Smith,</hi> alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Deprecation</hi> not the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint,</hi> God forgive them, for they have done me much harm. <hi>Envy</hi> that dark <hi>Shadow,</hi> always waiteth upon <hi>Shining Merit;</hi> being an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable <hi>Attendant</hi> of all good things: and where ſhe cannot find a hole, will be ſure to make one. I am ſure, in regard I venture to ſtand up in this <hi>Sycamore Tree,</hi> to be charg'd with <hi>Pride, Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>Arrogancy. Calumny</hi> and <hi>Conjecture</hi> may abuſe <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency</hi> her ſelf: But if <hi>God</hi> juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb facs="tcp:33585:6"/>
me in this <hi>Matter</hi> (as I believe he will) I fear not <hi>Mans Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> If I fall in with <hi>God,</hi> I care not who falls out with me. <hi>David</hi> was obedient to his <hi>Father's Commands,</hi> and took a great deal of pains to bring a <hi>Gift</hi> to the <hi>Captain</hi> to infavour his <hi>Brethren</hi> with him, and an <hi>Ephah</hi> of Parched Corn and ten loaves for their <hi>ſubſiſtance:</hi> When he had quit himſelf of that <hi>Burden,</hi> they laden him with another much harder to be born, <hi>Cruel Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> and <hi>Contumelious Words.</hi> I fear not that my <hi>Obedience</hi> to <hi>God</hi> will be <hi>in vain;</hi> but for my <hi>Care, Induſtry,</hi> and <hi>Kindneſs,</hi> to my <hi>Brethren,</hi> I ſhall have Inſtead of <hi>Grapes, Thorns;</hi> and for <hi>Figgs, Thiſtles.</hi> I have here provided and brought ſome <hi>Weapons</hi> which are not <hi>Carnal,</hi> not onely to oppoſe the <hi>Enemies</hi> that defie the <hi>Armies</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:7"/>
of the <hi>Living God,</hi> and exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> but ſuch as are Inſtrumental for the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it for our ſelves and for them that are under our charge: <hi>Matt.</hi> 11. 12. and alſo ſome <hi>Inſtructions</hi> how to manage them. I am ſure there is <hi>need</hi> enough, but the <hi>hearts</hi> of the <hi>need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> I am affraid are <hi>too proud</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of <hi>aſſiſtance;</hi> but will be ready to ask as the <hi>Captains</hi> that was with <hi>Jehu,</hi> did concerning he <hi>Prophet, Wherefore came this mad fellow</hi> hither? 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9. 11. I can find no better <hi>Anſwer</hi> for theſe <hi>Ingrato's</hi> than <hi>David</hi> gave his Brother, <hi>What have I now done? Is there not a Cauſe?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 29.</p>
            <p>How many are they, and what is moſt lamentable, who have taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> the <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> of <hi>God's Word</hi> and <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> to be <hi>Agents</hi> between <hi>God</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:7"/>
and his <hi>People,</hi> and to ſtand between the <hi>Porch</hi> and the <hi>Altar;</hi> who by preſuming to do what they are uncup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of, proſtitute the <hi>Solemnity</hi> of this <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Prayer;</hi> which being duly performed is the <hi>Sun</hi> of <hi>Spiritual Exerciſes,</hi> the <hi>Center</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> the <hi>Heart</hi> of <hi>Devotion,</hi> and the very <hi>Soul of Piety;</hi> but hy an <hi>undue performance</hi> of it, and by <hi>trifling</hi> in it, they render it <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable</hi> and <hi>contemptible,</hi> either by making a <hi>Set Form</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their <hi>weak apprehenſion</hi> of <hi>Things,</hi> or elſe, which is, <hi>more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable,</hi> to venture to pray <hi>extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> not having the Gift, nor any tollerable <hi>Requiſites</hi> or <hi>Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> towards it.</p>
            <p>This enſuing <hi>Work</hi> is principally intended for thoſe that pray in <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> and are as it were the <hi>Mouth</hi> of all that joyn with <hi>them:</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:33585:8"/>
               <hi>every one</hi> may inform <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> for the performance of <hi>Private Devotion,</hi> by the following <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have obſerved two great defects in <hi>Publick Extempore Prayer,</hi> the one <hi>Want</hi> of <hi>Method,</hi> and the other the <hi>Want</hi> of <hi>apt</hi> and <hi>elegant Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions;</hi> which even forc'd me upon this adventure.</p>
            <p>I own that the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> is from infuſion from above, and is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Miniſtration</hi> of the <hi>Spirit.</hi> But <hi>Method</hi> is the <hi>Organ,</hi> and <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Sweet-charming</hi> and <hi>Pathetical Expreſſions,</hi> are the <hi>Harmony;</hi> and where theſe all combine together, there's a <hi>Heavenly Melody.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Its well known that the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> generally worketh in the <hi>Uſe</hi> of <hi>Means:</hi> And when the <hi>Heart</hi> bath indited a <hi>Good Matter,</hi> cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the <hi>Tongue</hi> to be like unto the
<pb facs="tcp:33585:8"/>
               <hi>Pen</hi> of a <hi>Ready Writer.</hi> I have found that the <hi>Spirit</hi> is more aſſiſtant in <hi>Method</hi> than otherwiſe, for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion</hi> in the <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Thoughts</hi> hinder the <hi>Operation</hi> thereof: <hi>Method</hi> and <hi>Matter</hi> ought to be <hi>ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di'd</hi> and <hi>obſerved,</hi> by all <hi>Publick Perſons,</hi> as <hi>Miniſters, Chaplains, Maſters</hi> of <hi>Families, &amp;c.</hi> becauſe we are to work upon the <hi>Affections</hi> of <hi>them</hi> that joyn with <hi>us:</hi> I ſhall firſt ſpeak to the <hi>Method</hi> of <hi>Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In want of <hi>Method</hi> there muſt neceſſarily be great <hi>Irregularity,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Wandering</hi> and <hi>Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flat</hi> and <hi>baffle Devotion,</hi> and withal many times, as I have obſerved, ſome of the <hi>Eſſential Parts</hi> of <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> omitted; Yea by able <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and they who were accounted <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarly gifted</hi> for this <hi>perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> for want of <hi>Method,</hi> have ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly ſtepp'd out of one part of <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:9"/>
into another, and preſently hedg'd back again; and have been guilty of <hi>Notorious Tautology,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times being at <hi>Non-plus,</hi> rather than continue <hi>ſilent, pronounce</hi> that which they would be aſhamed to ſee in <hi>Writing:</hi> and in this <hi>hurry</hi> and <hi>diſorder</hi> forget the <hi>Confeſſing of Sin, Thankſgiving,</hi> or the <hi>Afflicted,</hi> or ſome other <hi>Things,</hi> which ought not to he left out. Theſe <hi>faults</hi> and <hi>neglects</hi> are not ſo conſiderable in <hi>Private Devotion,</hi> nor <hi>intermiſſion,</hi> which is intollerable in <hi>Publick.</hi> They ſay they pray by the <hi>Dictates</hi> of the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> and that <hi>Praying</hi> in <hi>Method</hi> is not much different from a <hi>Set Form,</hi> and that <hi>Set Forms</hi> are <hi>dull, heartleſs, lifeleſs.</hi> For my part, I find no Authority to condemn <hi>Set Forms</hi> of <hi>Prayer;</hi> neither will I <hi>judge</hi> or <hi>reproach</hi> any that pray one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by <hi>them;</hi> thoſe that are not <hi>gifted</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:9"/>
muſt do as they <hi>can.</hi> But <hi>Method</hi> and <hi>Form</hi> in my eye are two diſtinct <hi>Things,</hi> as in this my <hi>Deſign</hi> you will find. My <hi>Hearers</hi> know I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly keep a <hi>Method,</hi> altho I take liberty to vary <hi>Expreſſions</hi> every day, which I find much refreſhing to them as well as to my ſelf. I am ſo far from being obliged or obliging to a <hi>Pack</hi> of <hi>Words,</hi> that I would not have any to think me ſo vain, as to endeavour to bind any to keep to my <hi>Expreſſions;</hi> far be it from me to reduce all that may be ſpoken in this <hi>Duty</hi> to a <hi>proportion</hi> or <hi>ſcantling</hi> of my <hi>Conceiving:</hi> for I know, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>prophane World</hi> ſcoff, the <hi>Product</hi> of Divine Inſpiration, muſt be a great <hi>Sum</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Sanctity,</hi> which do not onely raviſh the hearts of them that poſſeſs them, but expandeth to the inlightening of all about them. It
<pb facs="tcp:33585:10"/>
was the <hi>emptineſs</hi> and <hi>inſufficiency</hi> of too many, that caus'd me to offer this which I call not a <hi>Form,</hi> but a <hi>Sample, Pattern,</hi> or <hi>Directory.</hi> I believe I ſhall many times perform this <hi>Duty,</hi> and not vſe any of theſe <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> I bleſs God there's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from whence theſe came; yet I obſerve a Method, even this which I ſhew to the world. I begin with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration,</hi> then to <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> from <hi>Confeſſion</hi> to <hi>Gratulation,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Petition</hi> in general; and afterward deſcend to particulars, for the <hi>Church,</hi> for <hi>Governours,</hi> for the <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel, for a Bleſſing upon the Word preached, for Unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate Men, for Wounded Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> for <hi>others</hi> in <hi>Affliction;</hi> and then conclude, rolling <hi>our ſelves</hi> upon <hi>God</hi> and committing <hi>our ſelves</hi> unto <hi>his Protection,</hi> with ſome <hi>Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Supplications</hi> for his guiding of
<pb facs="tcp:33585:10"/>
us and care over us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the uſing of this <hi>Method</hi> we ſhall not omit any <hi>part</hi> of <hi>Prayer.</hi> This is my <hi>way</hi> in my <hi>Meditations</hi> for the <hi>preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for the <hi>Duty</hi> and in <hi>performance</hi> of <hi>it,</hi> And my <hi>grounds</hi> for it are that we ought to fill our <hi>Apprehenſions</hi> and <hi>Underſtandings</hi> with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Great things</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Infiniteneſs</hi> of the <hi>Glory, Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Wiſdom, Power Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Purity</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> this will bring a <hi>Dread</hi> and <hi>Conſternation</hi> upon us; <hi>Then</hi> come to conſider his <hi>Grace, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Mercy, Truth, Sufficiency, &amp;c.</hi> this will temper the <hi>Conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> that the <hi>Conſideration</hi> of the more <hi>awful Attributes</hi> brought upon us: So there will be a <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Mixture</hi> of <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi> To have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, right <hi>Opinions</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſions</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> is the <hi>Architectonicon, Baſis,</hi> and <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:11"/>
of all <hi>Devotion.</hi> The <hi>Wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> upon <hi>God</hi> with a <hi>due ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>Nature, Attributes,</hi> and the <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> of his <hi>Providences,</hi> raiſeth our <hi>Minds,</hi> quickeneth our <hi>Affections,</hi> and cauſeth us to take all up the <hi>Hill</hi> to the <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> And when we have ſpent ſome time in this <hi>Exerciſe,</hi> in <hi>Adoring, Praiſing</hi> and <hi>Glorifying God,</hi> then look we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. I believe in <hi>Divinity</hi> as well as in <hi>Phyloſophy,</hi> The Knowledge of one <hi>Contrary</hi> bringeth in the <hi>Contrary</hi> or <hi>another:</hi> After we have conſider'd that all the <hi>Prodigies</hi> of <hi>Greatneſs</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> are in <hi>God,</hi> then to look upon and into our <hi>Selves,</hi> and conſider we are the <hi>Creatutes</hi> of the <hi>Moſt High, and what Obligations</hi> he hath laid upon us, and what kind of <hi>Returns</hi> we have made, what <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> are incumbent upon us, and how we have perform'd them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe
<pb facs="tcp:33585:11"/>
things done unfraudulently, will bring <hi>Confuſion</hi> upon our <hi>Faces;</hi> this muſt humble us, ay to the Earth. Theſe things being truly conſidered, maketh us ſick of our ſelves, and ſo to loath our ſelves, as to vomit up our <hi>Sin</hi> by <hi>Confeſſion;</hi> then we ſhall ſay in <hi>bitterneſs</hi> of <hi>Spirit</hi> (not in a <hi>Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical Manner,</hi> as the moſt do) <hi>That we have left undone thoſe things which we ought to have done:</hi> And <hi>That we have done thoſe things which we ought not to have done.</hi> We ſhall with deep <hi>accents</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments</hi> ſay we are miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for the nearer we draw to <hi>God</hi> the more <hi>light</hi> diſcovereth it ſelf; which will ſhew that <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>polu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in us that we were <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to, in reſpect of the <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of it. Then it neceſſarily followeth that we ſhall fall upon the <hi>Admiring</hi> and <hi>Praiſing God's Long-ſuffering,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:12"/>
               <hi>Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> that the <hi>effects</hi> of our <hi>Sins</hi> are not upon us; and acknowledge our <hi>Selves</hi> the <hi>Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing monuments</hi> of his <hi>Grace,</hi> and return <hi>Hearty Thanks</hi> for all the Bleſſings We enjoy <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral;</hi> knowing our <hi>Selves</hi> to be <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unworthy</hi> of them, and that 'tis meerly <hi>Divine Bounty</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth them. Then <hi>Free-grace</hi> will appear more <hi>beautiful</hi> than the <hi>Sun.</hi> Then the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> the great <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> thereof, will be the <hi>Chief</hi> of <hi>Ten thouſand:</hi> Then <hi>precious</hi> will the <hi>Promiſes</hi> and all the <hi>Means</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> appear: Certainly this is enough to make the <hi>Dumb</hi> to <hi>ſpeak,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large every <hi>ſtrait heart</hi> to give all <hi>poſſible thanks,</hi> and to <hi>ſtudy</hi> what they ſhall <hi>render</hi> unto the <hi>Lord</hi> for all his <hi>benefits.</hi> And by this time we ſhall be ſo high, lifted out of <hi>Worldly Darkneſs,</hi> that we ſhall ſee
<pb facs="tcp:33585:12"/>
what <hi>Guilt</hi> even the <hi>beſt</hi> of us <hi>gather</hi> and <hi>contract</hi> day by day; then ſhall we beg to be <hi>waſhed</hi> and <hi>purifi'd:</hi> Alſo we ſhall ſee our <hi>Frailty</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability,</hi> and be earneſt with <hi>God</hi> for ſuch <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Qualifications</hi> as ſhall inable us to run the <hi>Race</hi> that is <hi>ſet before us;</hi> and by conſidering other <hi>Mens conditions</hi> by our <hi>own,</hi> we ſhall not fail to intercede for <hi>them.</hi> This is the <hi>Method</hi> I conſtantly keep (I can ſay) with <hi>great benefit;</hi> but in the <hi>words</hi> of the great <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> If any one can Shew me a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Way, <hi>Noverint Univerſi,</hi> I am not of them that deſpiſe <hi>Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Want</hi> that I obſerv'd in the <hi>performance</hi> of this <hi>Duty,</hi> is the not having full and weighty <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> which is like the want of <hi>Wing-feathers</hi> to a <hi>Bird,</hi> or of a <hi>Gale</hi> of <hi>Wind</hi> to a <hi>Ship</hi> under ſail.
<pb facs="tcp:33585:13"/>
We ought to uſe <hi>full and ſignificant Words</hi> in <hi>Prayer,</hi> not ſo much to mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Mind of God</hi> by <hi>Rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Inſinuations,</hi> as by rehearſing and conſidering the <hi>Words,</hi> to ſtir up in our ſelves <hi>Attention, Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Contrition, Gratulation, Fervent Holy Deſires,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sinewy pregnant powerful Expreſſions,</hi> are an <hi>Advertiſement</hi> unto us, and that <hi>Advertiſement</hi> leadeth us unto <hi>a Conſideration,</hi> and the <hi>Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> carrieth us to the <hi>Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Rehearſing of <hi>Words</hi> are profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, if thereto the <hi>Mind</hi> give heed; then we pray with the <hi>Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> as <hi>St.</hi> Paul mentions; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 15. I have here provided many <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds</hi> of <hi>Expreſſions</hi> adapted and fitted for each part of <hi>Prayer,</hi> I could have placed them ſo that they might have been more <hi>dependant</hi> and <hi>coherent,</hi> but my <hi>Intention</hi> is not
<pb facs="tcp:33585:13"/>
to teach <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Prayer.</hi> I have laid them <hi>open,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> who have not the <hi>Gift</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> (for <hi>them</hi> this is chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended) may take and chooſe where <hi>they</hi> pleaſe, and with a <hi>little Induſtry</hi> ſo order their <hi>Affairs,</hi> that they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs <hi>themſelves</hi> with <hi>variety</hi> every time <hi>they</hi> are call'd to <hi>the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> of this <hi>Duty,</hi> to the great <hi>inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening</hi> and <hi>refreſhment</hi> of <hi>themſelves</hi> and <hi>others.</hi> I much fear <hi>that</hi> ſome of thoſe <hi>Raptures</hi> are ſo <hi>high</hi> and <hi>lofty,</hi> that they be obſcured in the <hi>Clouds</hi> of <hi>ſome Mens Ignorance;</hi> and to ſuch will prove <hi>invaluable:</hi> But I muſt, as they that ſhew their <hi>Jewels</hi> openly, abide the <hi>Curioſity</hi> and <hi>Cenſure</hi> of <hi>every Beholder:</hi> And ſurely by the <hi>Ignorant</hi> the <hi>Richeſt</hi> ſhall be the <hi>leaſt regarded, Judgments</hi> being <hi>apt to err</hi> where they <hi>paſs</hi> upon <hi>Things,</hi> they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not. We take <hi>Unknown Coyn,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:14"/>
ſuſpiciouſly, and where there is no <hi>true Judgment,</hi> the <hi>heaiveſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> cometh. I obſerve the <hi>Poets</hi> many times in their <hi>Prologues</hi> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly intreat to be <hi>underſtood,</hi> that is, that the <hi>Auditors</hi> and <hi>Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> may not <hi>Hiſs,</hi> untill they have <hi>well conſider'd</hi> and know a <hi>reaſon</hi> for it. One of them telleth the <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> why he maketh ſuch an <hi>Apologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some Critic woudbe's they will rail at the Poet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For ſpeaking ſenſe (poor ſouls) and they not know it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhew'd my <hi>Papers</hi> in <hi>Manuſcript</hi> to <hi>divers,</hi> who I preſumed were <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent</hi> and <hi>Learned,</hi> deſiring <hi>them</hi> to try <hi>them,</hi> and paſs <hi>Judgment,</hi> and <hi>execute them</hi> who deſerved not <hi>to live;</hi> To work they went, with <hi>Abbington Law:</hi> When I came to
<pb facs="tcp:33585:14"/>
ſee what <hi>condition</hi> my <hi>dear Iſſue</hi> was in, I found the chiefeſt of my <hi>Darl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> under <hi>Bars,</hi> being <hi>croſs'd out, ſentenced,</hi> ready for <hi>Execution.</hi> I not having patience to ſee the <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> barbarouſly murder'd before <hi>my face, Natural Affection</hi> (you know will do much) forced me to <hi>arreſt</hi> the <hi>Judgment,</hi> and by that means pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured another <hi>Tryal</hi> for them: But they being <hi>Strangers,</hi> ſpake in a <hi>Language</hi> that their <hi>Judges</hi> were not <hi>acquainted with,</hi> they never having been in the <hi>High Countreys,</hi> where the <hi>ſuppoſed Criminals</hi> came from: But with much ado I procured ſome <hi>Interpreters</hi> that underſtand <hi>both Languages,</hi> and cauſing ſome <hi>auxiliary Lights</hi> to be brought in, by and by the <hi>Innocents</hi> appear'd in great <hi>lovelineſs</hi> and <hi>beauty;</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that their <hi>haſty inconſiderate Judges</hi> imbraced <hi>them</hi> and did <hi>them</hi> great Honour.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:15"/>
I am well acquainted with the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>World,</hi> Pride and <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> thoſe <hi>inſeperable Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> go hand in hand next the <hi>Wall;</hi> and where ever they meet <hi>Divine Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Humility</hi> (who never part) they kick them into the <hi>Kennel.</hi> I have read of one kind of <hi>Serpent,</hi> that always <hi>hiſſes</hi> at the <hi>Light:</hi> I know what ſort of <hi>Men</hi> will uſe more <hi>Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm</hi> than <hi>Ability,</hi> another ſort that know better things, will look upon my <hi>pains</hi> and <hi>endeavours,</hi> as tho they look'd thro the <hi>wrong end</hi> of a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective,</hi> which maketh <hi>things</hi> ſeem <hi>little, inconſiderable,</hi> at <hi>great diſtance,</hi> and of <hi>little value: Others</hi> there are that are ſo <hi>proud</hi> that they'll rather <hi>ſit</hi> in the <hi>dark</hi> than <hi>light</hi> their <hi>Candle</hi> at their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> more I know that will not fail to throw <hi>dirt</hi> in my <hi>face,</hi> and endeavour to perſwade the <hi>World</hi> that its my <hi>Natural</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:15"/>
               <hi>Complexion;</hi> and will ſtrive to blaſt my <hi>Fruits</hi> with their <hi>poiſonous breath: O Tempora! O Mores!</hi> I have <hi>twenty years</hi> together run the <hi>Gauntlet,</hi> many a <hi>blow</hi> and <hi>thruſt</hi> I have had, yet (for all) thro <hi>mercy</hi> I am ſtill on my <hi>Leggs,</hi> and able to face <hi>them.</hi> We may know when we ſee <hi>a Tree</hi> batter'd, and <hi>ſtones</hi> and <hi>ſticks</hi> lying in the <hi>Boughs,</hi> that <hi>good Fruit</hi> hath grown <hi>there.</hi> Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the <hi>diſcouragments</hi> I have <hi>had</hi> and am ſure to <hi>meet</hi> with, I determine not <hi>to leave</hi> any <hi>thing</hi> undone that is <hi>incumbent</hi> upon me. It was a <hi>humble,</hi> but a <hi>ſweet</hi> and <hi>gracious Saying</hi> of a worthy Divine, <hi>I am glad to bring one Pin towards the decking of the Lords Bride.</hi> What ever is in <hi>my way</hi> that tendeth to <hi>Edification,</hi> or may in the leaſt help the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> I reſolve (by <hi>Gods help)</hi> to break thro the
<pb facs="tcp:33585:16"/>
               <hi>throngs</hi> of <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> to hand it to <hi>her;</hi> and if this be as <hi>kindly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted</hi> as it is <hi>humbly offered,</hi> it will <hi>vigorate</hi> me in the <hi>performance</hi> of <hi>that</hi> which is before me.</p>
            <p>Let no one think that I would have <hi>them</hi> to mutter over any of theſe <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions</hi> in <hi>Prayer</hi> without <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> as tho there were ſome <hi>Magical force</hi> in them; I intend <hi>them</hi> not for <hi>ſuch: God</hi> delighteth not in the <hi>Sacrifices</hi> of <hi>Fools.</hi> Surely there is not any that oftner <hi>proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> againſt <hi>heartleſs performances</hi> than I do. I have often <hi>ſaid,</hi> yet I find not any <hi>reaſon</hi> to <hi>recant</hi> it, <hi>That God is more diſpleas'd with the unſincere Prayers of the Wicked, than with any other of their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> It's an old <hi>Saying, Simulata ſanctitas eſt duplex Iniquitas.</hi> It's much better <hi>not to tread</hi> the <hi>Lords Courts</hi> at all, than <hi>in vain.</hi> What
<pb facs="tcp:33585:16"/>
a heavy <hi>Deteſtation God</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in the Firſt of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> againſt <hi>Vain Oblations,</hi> and againſt their <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical ſpreading forth their hands. Heartleſs Operations</hi> are <hi>hearty Diſſimulations.</hi> How <hi>the Amen, the faithful and true Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the beginning of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God,</hi> loath'd the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Laodicea;</hi> Revel. 3. 14, 15, 16. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of her <hi>luke-warmneſs:</hi> He wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhe were either <hi>cold</hi> or <hi>hot;</hi> that is either to ſerve him in <hi>ſincerity,</hi> or not <hi>to pretend</hi> to it: but becauſe ſhe was <hi>luke-warm,</hi> he <hi>ſpew'd</hi> her out of his <hi>Mouth</hi> with <hi>ſtrong demonſtration</hi> of <hi>abhorrency:</hi> And how far it is from <hi>God</hi> to return to his <hi>Vomit</hi> again: <hi>God</hi> will not <hi>be mock'd,</hi> Good <hi>Words</hi> without the <hi>heart are</hi> but <hi>Flattery,</hi> yea good <hi>Works</hi> without the <hi>Heart</hi> are but <hi>Hyprocriſie.</hi> I confeſs <hi>Prayer</hi> is a Sacrifice, but <hi>abominable,</hi> except
<pb facs="tcp:33585:17"/>
the <hi>Heart</hi> be the <hi>Altar,</hi> whereon it is offered. <hi>A Heart</hi> without a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> is better than a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> without a <hi>Heart. Deus magis delectat af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu quam effectu;</hi> is an Old but true <hi>Maxime</hi> in <hi>Divinity. God</hi> calleth for the <hi>heart,</hi> Pro. 23. 26. He that is <hi>all</hi> in <hi>all</hi> to <hi>us,</hi> will have <hi>all</hi> in <hi>all</hi> in <hi>us;</hi> as the famous <hi>Carthaginian Captain</hi> was <hi>Primus ingreſſus and ulitmus egreſſus;</hi> ſo our <hi>Hearts</hi> muſt be the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>laſt</hi> in all our <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's ſad to <hi>conſider</hi> that the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> ſhould give <hi>real honour</hi> to <hi>counterfeit gods,</hi> and that <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſhould give <hi>a counterfeit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> to the <hi>True God.</hi> A <hi>Sacrifice</hi> without a <hi>Heart</hi> was a <hi>ſad</hi> and <hi>Omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Preſage</hi> in the <hi>Superſtition</hi> of the <hi>Roman Augurs.</hi> They that give but the <hi>Skin</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> ſhall have but the <hi>Shell</hi> of <hi>Comfort. He</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:17"/>
that accepteth the <hi>Heart</hi> without any <hi>thing,</hi> will not accept of <hi>any thing</hi> without the <hi>Heart.</hi> I have heard of a <hi>Gentlemans Servant,</hi> that was ſuch an <hi>Ignoramo,</hi> that when he heard that his <hi>Mother</hi> was offended with his <hi>negligence</hi> in not ſending of <hi>her a Letter,</hi> ſent <hi>her</hi> a <hi>Letter</hi> that came for his <hi>Maſter;</hi> thinking if it were a <hi>Letter</hi> it was well <hi>enough,</hi> what ever was <hi>in it;</hi> which did not onely <hi>diſcover</hi> his own <hi>folly</hi> but affront his <hi>Mother.</hi> Too many ſuch <hi>Ignoramo's</hi> have we, that hear <hi>God</hi> expecteth <hi>Sacrifices</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Praiſe,</hi> and to hear daily from <hi>them;</hi> then they get ſome other <hi>Mens Letters,</hi> ſuch as <hi>others</hi> have <hi>made</hi> and <hi>directed</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> not conſidering the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents</hi> of them, but offer them at a <hi>venture,</hi> their <hi>hearts</hi> being <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to <hi>them:</hi> which doth not onely ſhew
<pb facs="tcp:33585:18"/>
their <hi>wretched Ignorance,</hi> but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronteth the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> as tho he were not acquainted with all our <hi>ways</hi> nor pondered all our <hi>goings. Vain Prayers</hi> are <hi>Religioſum Scelus,</hi> which indeed are <hi>Wickedneſſes</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Magnitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore in the <hi>words</hi> of the <hi>Wiſe man</hi> Iexhort <hi>thee,</hi> When <hi>thou prayeſt,</hi> prepare thine Heart, and be not as <hi>one</hi> that tempteth the <hi>Lord.</hi> He alludeth to an <hi>Irreverent Fellow</hi> that ruſheth inconſiderately into a <hi>Princes preſence,</hi> which tempteth the <hi>Prince</hi> to <hi>order him</hi> to be <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> How <hi>many</hi> in <hi>this Kingdom</hi> daily thus tempt <hi>God,</hi> by their <hi>inconſiderate entring</hi> into this <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> being not ſo much concern'd as they who <hi>worſhip Idols.</hi> How <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable</hi> it is to go into a <hi>Church,</hi> when the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is at <hi>Prayer,</hi> and the People about him, ſcarce one
<pb facs="tcp:33585:18"/>
of them ſhewing any <hi>Reſpect, Reve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence, Affection,</hi> or <hi>Devotion,</hi> their eyes wandering from one part of the <hi>Congregation</hi> to another, the <hi>Men</hi> adjuſting of their <hi>Hair</hi> or <hi>Peruque,</hi> and the other <hi>Sex,</hi> their <hi>Ornaments;</hi> ſome <hi>whiſpering,</hi> others in <hi>intoler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Poſtures,</hi> yet will obſerve their <hi>times</hi> to give their <hi>Reſponds,</hi> and ſpeak to <hi>God</hi> when they do not <hi>think</hi> of <hi>him.</hi> Theſe are <hi>they</hi> that <hi>God complaineth of, That draw near unto him with their lipps, when their hearts are far from him.</hi> I plead not for <hi>outward Poſtures</hi> and <hi>Geſtures,</hi> yet I am ſure if the <hi>heart</hi> be <hi>rightly affected,</hi> it <hi>commandeth</hi> the <hi>Body.</hi> When the <hi>Mind</hi> is fill'd with what concerneth us in the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance</hi> of this <hi>Duty,</hi> we are far from <hi>notifying</hi> other <hi>Trifles:</hi> How many <hi>there are</hi> that think they have performed their <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:19"/>
when <hi>they</hi> have rabbl'd over a <hi>many words,</hi> altho <hi>they</hi> have no more <hi>ſenſe</hi> or <hi>knowledg</hi> of what <hi>they ſay,</hi> then <hi>Parrots</hi> have.</p>
            <p>I have read of one <hi>Bolus,</hi> an <hi>Actor</hi> upon a <hi>Stage,</hi> in the <hi>Repreſentation</hi> of <hi>Grief,</hi> he feign'd a <hi>Weeping,</hi> but at the <hi>very time,</hi> he remembred the <hi>death</hi> of <hi>his onely Daughter</hi> then he <hi>weep'd in earneſt:</hi> I wiſh that our ordinary Actors, when they ſay daily, <hi>We have left undone thoſe things that we ought to have done, and done thoſe things which we ought not to have done, and that there is no health in us,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>words</hi> are good, and above <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception,</hi> as indeed in <hi>my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is all the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> I wiſh that they that <hi>daily uſe it,</hi> did but <hi>feel</hi> the <hi>weight</hi> of the <hi>words,</hi> and that their <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings</hi> did go along with their
<pb facs="tcp:33585:19"/>
               <hi>Tongues,</hi> and remember what they <hi>ſpeak</hi> is <hi>true,</hi> they would be <hi>ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> indeed. When we ſay, <hi>We have left undone thoſe things that we ought to have done;</hi> We ſay <hi>in effect</hi> we have not <hi>paid</hi> that <hi>Fear, Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Reverence, Honour, Praiſe, Love, Obedience,</hi> &amp;c. that is <hi>due</hi> from <hi>us</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> nor that <hi>Love, Pity, Charity,</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> that is due to our <hi>Neighbours.</hi> And when we ſay, <hi>That we have done thoſe things that we ought not to have done;</hi> that is, we <hi>have made</hi> unto our <hi>ſelves</hi> other <hi>Gods;</hi> that we have imagined <hi>Security</hi> in <hi>tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory things,</hi> prophaned the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Saboths;</hi> that our <hi>lives</hi> have been <hi>diſorderly,</hi> in <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, Cruelty, Incontinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Rapine, Perfidiouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Coveteouſneſs:</hi> and when we ſay, <hi>There is no health in us;</hi> We own
<pb facs="tcp:33585:20"/>
that our <hi>Brain</hi> is the <hi>Forge</hi> of <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs,</hi> our <hi>Eyes</hi> full of <hi>Adultery,</hi> our <hi>Tongues</hi> unruly <hi>Evils,</hi> full of <hi>deadly Poiſon;</hi> our <hi>Throats</hi> open <hi>Sepulchres,</hi> our <hi>Hearts deceitful</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>meaſure,</hi> and <hi>deſperately wicked;</hi> yea all our <hi>Members</hi> the <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> of <hi>Iniquity:</hi> Now if our <hi>Conſiciences</hi> were but as ready, as active as <hi>Nathan</hi> was to <hi>David,</hi> and tell us, yea convince every one of us, that <hi>thou art the Man,</hi> that hath contracted all this <hi>guilt,</hi> and art ſo <hi>wretched;</hi> and <hi>God</hi> darting in <hi>ſome beams</hi> of <hi>Divine light,</hi> as he <hi>commonly doth</hi> when we <hi>wait</hi> upon <hi>him</hi> in <hi>ſincerity,</hi> this would make us turn our <hi>formalities</hi> into <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</hi> I muſt ſay, I have had many times a <hi>warm heart</hi> full of <hi>Devotion</hi> in <hi>reading</hi> the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> by fetching and binding my <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> to the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>words.</hi> I
<pb facs="tcp:33585:20"/>
own their <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> that were the <hi>Compilers</hi> of it, but think it's <hi>impoſſible</hi> to perſwade me, that they ever intended to <hi>blind</hi> and <hi>oblige Gifted Men</hi> ſo to it, as not to exerciſe <hi>their Indowments.</hi> Neither do I find that the <hi>Governours</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> pretend to it.</p>
            <p>It was a <hi>ſweet Admonition</hi> of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians, Neither to give offence to the Jew, nor to the Gentile, nor to the Church of God: God</hi> knoweth my <hi>endeavors</hi> are for <hi>Love, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Unity.</hi> I have been very careful in my <hi>Studies</hi> not to write <hi>any thing</hi> that could give <hi>juſt offence.</hi> If any thing in this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> ſeem to be <hi>too ſevere,</hi> and that there are too many <hi>grating Reflections,</hi> ſo far as I know my own <hi>heart,</hi> the <hi>Arrows</hi> I have ſhot, I ſent them with a <hi>good will,</hi> not for <hi>ruin,</hi> but <hi>remedy:</hi> Why ſhall I not
<pb facs="tcp:33585:21"/>
meet with a <hi>Candid Interpretation?</hi> But if otherwiſe, I determine to be <hi>purely paſſive,</hi> and receive all the <hi>Scorn, Contempt,</hi> or what elſe can come, with an <hi>indeclinable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſcence</hi> in the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that will e'r long diſcover the <hi>ſecrets</hi> of all <hi>hearts.</hi> In the interim I doubt not but theſe my <hi>labours</hi> and <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours,</hi> will be a <hi>Guide</hi> and <hi>Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> to many, that are <hi>hungering</hi> and <hi>thirſting</hi> after <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> that are <hi>inquiring, Where Chriſt feedeth, and where his Flocks reſt at Noon day?</hi> That wait for <hi>Wiſdom</hi> as they that watch for the <hi>Morning.</hi> But let no one <hi>ſpeak</hi> to <hi>God</hi> by mine or any other <hi>Directions,</hi> except the <hi>heart</hi> ſpeak the <hi>words,</hi> and the <hi>words</hi> the <hi>heart:</hi> And that you may ſo do, I'll but open one <hi>Text</hi> of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and conclude this: It is in Joſhua 15. 16. <hi>And</hi> Caleb <hi>ſaid,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:21"/>
               <hi>He that ſmiteth</hi> Kirjath-ſepher, <hi>and taketh it, to him will I give</hi> Achſach <hi>my Daughter to Wife.</hi> This <hi>Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jath-ſepher</hi> was a <hi>City</hi> in <hi>Canaan,</hi> that held out after that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had got <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Land; Caleb,</hi> ſeeing it to be very deſirable, and moſt neceſſary for them, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth his Daughter <hi>Achſach,</hi> which was very <hi>beautiful</hi> and <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> as a <hi>Reward</hi> to any one that ſhould take <hi>Kirjath-ſepher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What chiefly concerneth me to <hi>open</hi> to <hi>you,</hi> is, What this <hi>Kirjath-ſepher</hi> and <hi>Achſach,</hi> and how to apply them in a <hi>Spiritual Senſe; Kirjath-ſepher</hi> ſignifieth <hi>the Strong-hold of the Letter,</hi> and <hi>Achſach, the Rending of the Vail;</hi> ſo whoſoever <hi>ſmiteth</hi> and <hi>taketh</hi> the <hi>Strong-hold</hi> of the <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Divine Truths;</hi> ſhall have the <hi>Rending</hi> of the <hi>Vail:</hi> That is, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33585:22"/>
               <hi>ſhall find out the ſpiritual Meaning of the things written in Scripture, or elſe-where, that are Divine; ſhall have the Vail rent that is between us, and the things that are ſpiritually diſcerned, and we ſhall ſee into the beauty of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reader, Conſider the <hi>Letter</hi> kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, but the <hi>Spirit</hi> giveth life: Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever depends upon the <hi>External Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances</hi> of <hi>Outward Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> or the <hi>Hiſtorical Knowledge</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> for their <hi>Salvation,</hi> will ſurely meet with ſuch diſappointment that <hi>death</hi> inſtead of <hi>life</hi> will be their <hi>portion.</hi> Therefore whatever thou doſt, gain <hi>Kirjath-ſepher,</hi> there lieth all the <hi>Treaſure,</hi> then <hi>Ach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſach</hi> will ſurely be thine, that <hi>Vail</hi> which covereth thy <hi>Face</hi> whilſt thou art a <hi>Stranger</hi> to the <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> ſhall be rent, and thou wilt ſee that
<pb facs="tcp:33585:22"/>
which will make thee cry out, Pſal. 84. 1, 2, 10. <hi>How aimable are thy Tabernacles, O Lord of Hoſts, My Soul longeth, yea, even fainteth for the Courts of the Lord. One day in thy Courts, is better then a Thouſand elſe where,</hi> &amp;c. And the <hi>Vail</hi> that covereth thy <hi>Face,</hi> ſhall not only be rent, but the <hi>Vail</hi> that covereth thy <hi>Heart;</hi> thou wilt not only ſee of the <hi>Divine Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies</hi> that are in <hi>God,</hi> and a <hi>Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gah's Proſpect,</hi> but thou wilt ſee that <hi>Den</hi> and <hi>Cave</hi> of <hi>Uncleaneſs,</hi> the <hi>deeps</hi> of <hi>Filth</hi> that is in thy own <hi>Heart;</hi> which will cauſe <hi>Gods Mercy</hi> to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing, and thee reſtleſs until thou be <hi>partaker</hi> of it: by thy gaining of <hi>Achſach</hi> thou wilt ſee the things that are ſpiritually diſcern'd. Take one <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Advice</hi> how to go about this great <hi>Work,</hi> and God ſpeed thee well. When thou readeſt that <hi>God</hi> is the
<pb facs="tcp:33585:23"/>
               <hi>Omnipotent Lord of all Glory and Majeſty,</hi> make way through thy Thoughts and Conſiderations, to thy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, and entertain the <hi>Notion</hi> there, and let it be an <hi>Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant</hi> with thee, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith concerning the <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> I ſay of the <hi>Knowledg of him, Hold it faſt, and grow old therein:</hi> This will make thee reverence <hi>Him,</hi> his Name will be great in thy ſight; and when thou readeſt, <hi>He's the great Benefactor of Mankind,</hi> &amp;c. Obſerve the former <hi>Method</hi> in bringing the <hi>Notion</hi> home, this will exceedingly greaten thy <hi>Reſpect</hi> and increaſe thy <hi>Love</hi> to him. And when thou readeſt, <hi>That we have prophaned our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which are due onely to God, by ſetting them upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy things,</hi> and <hi>that our Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries are between our Breaſts:</hi> Conſider thou art the <hi>Man</hi> that hath
<pb facs="tcp:33585:23"/>
promiſed to forſake the <hi>Devil,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and thy ſelf only to thy <hi>great Lord,</hi> to love him with all thy <hi>Heart,</hi> and <hi>Mind,</hi> and <hi>Soul;</hi> and finding thy ſelf guilty, if thou have not an harden'd Whore's fore-head, thou muſt bluſh, and be confoundedly aſhamed, and acknowledg it <hi>Juſtice</hi> to be put away. And when thou readeſt, <hi>That we have continually lived in contempt of God and in the tranſgreſſion of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; breaking his bands in ſunder, laying the Reins of our Loyalty upon the Neck of licentious liberty:</hi> Conſider then what it is for the ſo much obliged <hi>Creature</hi> to rebel againſt ſo great and good <hi>Creator, Redeemer, Suſtainer,</hi> and <hi>Preſerver,</hi> and reckon thy ſelf in the throng of ſuch <hi>Malefactors;</hi> then thou canſt not be keep'd from judging and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring thy ſelf; and thus apprehending of the <hi>Soul</hi> of the <hi>Letter,</hi> taking <hi>Kirjath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſepher,</hi> thou wilt find ſo much within the <hi>Word</hi> which is <hi>Divine,</hi> that will rightly humble thee; when thou comeſt to <hi>Gratulation,</hi> ſo much <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> in <hi>Mercy,</hi> and ſo much <hi>Comfort</hi> in <hi>Grace,</hi> that will take and hold thee; that as <hi>Death</hi> is ſwallowed up in <hi>Victory,</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:33585:24"/>
thy <hi>Miſerable Wretchedneſs</hi> is ſwallowd up in <hi>Divine Bounty.</hi> And when thou haſt taken <hi>Kirjath-ſepher,</hi> and obtained <hi>Achſach,</hi> thou wilt find that every <hi>good</hi> and <hi>perfect Gift</hi> cometh from the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> and that thou wanteſt nothing that he hath not for thee; that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth <hi>himſelf</hi> in ſhewing <hi>Mercy</hi> and doing <hi>Good:</hi> this will incourage thee to lift up thy head upon the account of thy <hi>Redeemer,</hi> and with boldneſs ask Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. And when thou haſt taken <hi>Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jath-ſepher</hi> and injoy'd <hi>Achſach,</hi> thou wilt ſee the <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> her Ruins and Wants, and what is needful for her: Alſo the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Miniſters,</hi> what <hi>Bleſſing</hi> we want upon the <hi>Word Preached;</hi> alſo the <hi>Deplorable State</hi> of <hi>Unregenerate Men,</hi> and the <hi>Flaſhes</hi> of <hi>Hell Fire,</hi> that <hi>irreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibly</hi> invade the <hi>Wounded Soul;</hi> and ſee others in <hi>outward Troubles,</hi> bleeding by the <hi>Arrows</hi> of <hi>Gods Fury,</hi> and ſqueez'd in the <hi>Preſs</hi> of <hi>Adverſity,</hi> then thou wilt as <hi>Elihu,</hi> feel thy ſelf full of <hi>Matter,</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> within thee will conſtrain thee. When thou art ſeriouſly and divinely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, forget not thy <hi>Director,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>NICO. PEARSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:24"/>
            <head>ON THE AUTHOR AND HIS Elaborate Work.</head>
            <l>WHil'ſt the dull clods of worſe informed Earth</l>
            <l>Stifle the Spirit in its very birth;</l>
            <l>See here the more refined mould aſpire</l>
            <l>To Heaven which made it, in the Flaming fire</l>
            <l>Of Ardent zeal, to Praiſe, and Pray to him,</l>
            <l>That firſt endew'd the glorious <hi>Seraphim:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With Love like his he would not be alone,</l>
            <l>But ſhews the way to others to that Throne</l>
            <l>Whoſe Monarch bleſſeth all: but yet commands,</l>
            <l>His Creatures Prayers to force it from his hands:</l>
            <l>And ſhew'd the piercing Author to diſpence</l>
            <l>Methods to take even Heaven by violence.</l>
            <l>Which if by his Direction we attain,</l>
            <l>He hath the trouble, and we have the gain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:25"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33585:25"/>
            <head>THE RAPTURES OF A Flaming Spirit.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>ADORATION.</head>
               <p>ETernally Bleſſed, Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, moſt Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and moſt Glorious Lord our God.</p>
               <p>The high and lofty One, who inhabiteth Eternity, whoſe Name is Holy; who dwelleth in the high and holy Place.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:33585:26"/>
The Almighty Maker of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, and of all Things Viſible and Inviſible.</p>
               <p>Heaven is thy Throne, Earth is thy Foot-ſtool.</p>
               <p>Thou art incircled with Millions of Angels, cloathed with Glory and Honour, deck'd with Majeſty and Excellency, and arrayed with Beauty and Splendor.</p>
               <p>Before thee the glorious Angels cover their Faces, not being able to behold ſo glorious a Majeſty.</p>
               <p>Thy Throne is Ineſtimable, thy Glory Incomprehenſible, befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thee the Hoſt of Angels ſtand with trembling.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33585:26"/>
The Firſt Cauſe of Things, the Foundation of the Univerſe, the Infinite, Inviſible, and onely Wiſe God.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt no partner in thy Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Soveraignty.</p>
               <p>Thou, even thou, art Lord alone.</p>
               <p>Who dwelleſt in the Splendors of that inacceſſible Light, unto which no mortal eye can approach.</p>
               <p>Who with a powerful hand keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt an undiſturb'd Order in all thy Affairs.</p>
               <p>The Inviſible Divinity, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be comprehended within the ſcanty compaſs of a Created Mind.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:33585:27"/>
We thy poor Creatures with all Reverence deſire to lift up our dim eyes to diſcover ſome of the light of thy Perfections, to enkindle in our dull Souls ſome Devotion.</p>
               <p>Nothing can be added unto thee to make thee more excellent.</p>
               <p>Thou art eternal and infinite in Being and Perfection, who conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of thy ſelf alone, without parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation from others; being abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute endleſs, and without all limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Perfection; who deriveſt from thy own incomprehenſible Infiniteneſs, certain limited Natures and Perfections to Creatures, which Natures and Perfections in Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, are nothing elſe but little Particles and Participations of that Bottomleſs Sea of Infiniteneſs that is in thy Self; whereunto they all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33585:27"/>
are to be referr'd and reduced, as the Beam to the Sun, or as the Brook to the Spring.</p>
               <p>Thou art <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> and beſide thee there is no God.</p>
               <p>The Omnipotent Lord of all Glory and Majeſty, more high than all that can be imagined and conceived, and all that can be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood and conſider'd, with any Created Underſtanding. More, high and precious than all that can be beloved, enjoy'd, or deſired; for the Infiniteneſs of thy Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth far paſs and exceed all this; for thou art to all Creatures Incomprehenſible: no Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can reach unto thee, nor Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination nor Reaſon, nor any other Vertue created can comprehend thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:33585:28"/>
Thou haſt thy Exiſtence from thy Self and not from another; ſuch a Being, as in compariſon of thee nothing elſe hath a being. Who haſt no Succeſſion, always the ſame.</p>
               <p>Thou our God, art the Cauſe of Cauſes, and the Being of Beings; and in every Degree unſpeakable and incomprehenſible.</p>
               <p>How can we expreſs thy Noble Acts, or ſpeak out all thy Praiſe.</p>
               <p>Thy Name alone is excellent.</p>
               <p>Thou incomparably exceedeſt our beſt conceptions of thee.</p>
               <p>Thou holdeſt back the Face of thy Throne, and ſpreadeſt thy Cloud upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:33585:28"/>
When we endeavour to make Diſcoveries of thee, we ſtrain our ſight, thou betakeſt thy ſelf to thy heights.</p>
               <p>Thy Glory can neither be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted nor increaſed.</p>
               <p>Who hath ſeen thee, that he may tell us; and who can magnifie thee as thou art?</p>
               <p>As thou art of purer Eyes than to behold iniquity, ſo we are of impurer eyes than to behold thy glory.</p>
               <p>As the Heavens are above the Earth, ſo are thy thoughts above our thoughts, and thy ways above our ways.</p>
               <p>Thou art that fix'd and unſhaken
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33585:29"/>
Entity, that art without the leaſt ſhadow of variation.</p>
               <p>All certainty floweth from thee, from that Original Immutability that is in thy Self.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt an Independent, an Eternal Certainty, thou beholdeſt all Beings and Motions of Beings, paſt, preſent, and to come.</p>
               <p>Thou art the Reaſon and Order of all Things, that with everlaſting Laws do'ſt govern the World.</p>
               <p>Thou from the beginning haſt commanded Times to run, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Order, governing them by the Coeleſtial Bodies, which thou haſt placed; obliging them to obſerve an abſolute Harmony and Decorum in all their Motions,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33585:29"/>
to keep time with thy Muſical Laws.</p>
               <p>Thou compoſed'ſt all their Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and meaſured'ſt all their Dances.</p>
               <p>Thou art moſt neceſſarily and eternally exiſting, exalted in thy own ſtrength above the higheſt reach of our imaginations.</p>
               <p>In thee are all things, through thee are all things, and to thee are all things; the beginning from which, and the end to which all things do tend.</p>
               <p>Thou art Inexhauſtible in thy Sufficiency, Infinite in thy Good Will, who canſt ſupply all our Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, expecting no return, but is our benefit to give.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33585:30"/>
Heaven and Earth, and all that in them is, depend upon thee, as the Beams depend upon the Sun.</p>
               <p>Unto thee the whole World is infinitely obliged.</p>
               <p>Thou art that moſt Glorious and Super-eſſential Being of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that delighteſt thy ſelf with ſcattering of Beams, and in filling all things with th' Expandings and Circumfuſions of thy Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>In thy Hand is the Soul of every Living Thing, and the Breath of all Mankind.</p>
               <p>Thou art the Life of our Lives, and the Soul of our Souls.</p>
               <p>Thy Love is always bubbling and ſpringing out of thy ſelf, and over-flowing out to all.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33585:30"/>
Thou fanneſt thy Favors forth, to the Refreſhing and Delight of Heaven and Earth.</p>
               <p>Thou watereſt the Hills from thy Chambers, and ſatisfieſt the Earth with the Fruit of thy Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p>Thou crowneſt the year with thy Goodneſs, and thy Paths drop Fatneſs.</p>
               <p>Thou art the Source of the Springs of <hi>Lebanus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All things by a graduate Deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, receive their life, light, and being from thee.</p>
               <p>There is no Water in our Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns but what comes from thy Fountain.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:33585:31"/>
Thou art that high and infinite Spring, that always floweth out and is not impaired.</p>
               <p>Thou art the Treaſure of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth.</p>
               <p>Thy over-flowing Favors are not given one by one, but liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſtowed with an open hand.</p>
               <p>There is not any thing that hath any patrimony or being but what it hath from thee.</p>
               <p>The Eyes of all wait upon thee, and thou giveſt them their Meat in due ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>There is nothing Infinite, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and Perfect, but thy Self, who art the Perfection of all things.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:33585:31"/>
Thou art that Eſſential and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Goodneſs, Good not by Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but by Eſſence; whoſe Nature is Goodneſs it ſelf.</p>
               <p>In thee are Oceans of Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, being the Perfection of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p>In thee all Perfections are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>center'd.</p>
               <p>All Glory is hatch'd in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of God.</p>
               <p>All the Beauty, all Excellencies that lie ſcatter'd about in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are but drops of thy Ocean, beams of thy Sun, glympſes of thy Beauty.</p>
               <p>All the worth that is in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, dependeth abſolutely upon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33585:32"/>
thee, the higheſt End of all things whatſoever.</p>
               <p>The Rays of thy Goodneſs inli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens all things.</p>
               <p>Thou incompaſſeſt the World with thy out-ſtretched Arms, and reacheſt Perſeverance, to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Creation.</p>
               <p>Thou filleſt all things without inlarging thy ſelf, thou paſſeſt thro all things without moving of thy ſelf: Thou dwelleſt in all things without ſtraitning thy ſelf, thou createdſt all things without any neceſſity, thou governeſt all things without any travel, thou changeſt all things without any change to thy ſelf; thou judgeſt without error, thou puniſheſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſſion, and giveſt to all things
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33585:32"/>
continually, without exhauſting thy Treaſures.</p>
               <p>There is nothing ſo little that declareth not thy greatneſs, there is nothing ſo great that muſt not acknowledge thy Soveraignty, there is nothing ſo low that lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us not up to acknowledge thy Majeſty, and nothing ſo high that deſcendeth not down to teach us thy Verity.</p>
               <p>Thou our God art every way as full in all Goodneſs as thou art ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in Glory.</p>
               <p>Thou art not only to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd and adored for the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies that are in thy ſelf, but as the Benign Parent of all things, and the great Benefactor of Mankind.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33585:33"/>
Every good and perfect Gift cometh from thee the Father of Lights.</p>
               <p>All cauſes of Love and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can excite Deſire are in thee.</p>
               <p>We cannot deſire any thing that is Good that our God hath not for us.</p>
               <p>Thou that ſatisfieſt the immenſe deſires of the Angels, canſt anſwer all the deſires of our Souls in a moſt eminent manner unto all Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Thou art the moſt Soul-ſuitable and Soul-ſatisfying Good.</p>
               <p>If we ſtrain out the Quinteſſence of the Creature, or if we extract the moſt Exquiſite Spirit, it turns
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33585:33"/>
into froth; but in thee is unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Satisfaction.</p>
               <p>If we ask Bread of the World, it gives us a Stone; if we look for a Fiſh, we ſhall have a Serpent; and when we wait for an Egg, we ſhall not fail of a Scorpion: We come not only off with Vanities of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, but with Vexation of Spirit; but in thy Favour is Life. Thy Loving Kindneſs is better than Life it ſelf.</p>
               <p>In thee is all poſſible Good what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: All Good Things are in thee originally, eſſentially, equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, purely, immutably, infinitely, and eternally.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt All ſufficiency in thy Self, for thy Self, and for all thy Creatures.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33585:34"/>
The Inexhauſtible Fountain of all Conſolations.</p>
               <p>In thee are Oceans of Comfort, thou haſt Light to inlighten us, Wiſdom to counſel us, Power to ſupport us, Mercy to pardon us, Glory to raviſh us, and Fulneſs to fill us.</p>
               <p>When thou art abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, thou art immeaſurably lovely. The moſt attractive Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Inſatiable Love and all Aimable Excellencies, are emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentiy and tranſcendently trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant in thee eternally.</p>
               <p>There is no end of thy Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, no numbring of thy Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, nor fathoming thy Bounty.</p>
               <p>Thou art the Spring of Being,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33585:34"/>
the Root of Life, the Father of Wiſdom, the Fountain of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the Haven of Deſire.</p>
               <p>Thine is the Greatneſs, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, the Glory, and the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</p>
               <p>Thou art moſt worthy to be known, becauſe thou art the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Truth; moſt worthy of our love, becauſe thou art the chiefeſt Good; moſt worthy of our fear, becauſe thou art moſt powerful: moſt worthy of our obedience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art the moſt righteous Lawgiver, and moſt worthy of our truſt and confidence, becauſe thou art immutably Faithful.</p>
               <p>The Mountains ſhall depart, and the Hills ſhall be removed, but thy Kindneſs ſhall not depart from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33585:35"/>
thee; the Covenant of thy Peace ſhall not fail.</p>
               <p>It is better to truſt in God, than to have any confidence in Man. It is better to truſt in God than to have confidence in Princes.</p>
               <p>Thy Faithfulneſs is well-known in the Congregation of Saints.</p>
               <p>They that know thee, put their truſt in thee, becauſe thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt not them that ſeek thee.</p>
               <p>Thou art the Hope of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Saviour thereof in a time of trouble, the Strength of their Heart, and their Portion for ever.</p>
               <p>Thou art known for a Refuge in the Palaces of thy City, for thou art their mighty Protection and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33585:35"/>
ſtrong Ground, a Succour from Stumbling, and a Help from Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
               <p>Thou fulfilleſt the Deſires of them that fear thee, thou heareſt their Cry, and art a preſent Help in trouble.</p>
               <p>Thou art the beſt Refuge in the midſt of Storms, and the beſt Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to all afflicted Spirits.</p>
               <p>How excellent is thy loving-kindneſs, O Lord, therefore thy people put their truſt under the ſhadow of thy Wings.</p>
               <p>As the Heavens are above the Earth, ſo great is thy Love unto them that fear thee: Thou art their God for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:33585:36"/>
Who is God ſave the Lord? Who is a Rock ſave our God? Good and plenteous in mercy to all them that call upon him.</p>
               <p>Thou rideſt upon the Heavens in thine Excellency for the help of thy people; thou art their refuge, and underneath them are his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Arms.</p>
               <p>As the Mountains are about <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> ſo the Lord is about his people, even for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>Thy way O God is in the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, who is ſo great a God as our God; thou art a God that do'ſt Wonders; thou haſt declared thy Strength among tha people.</p>
               <p>There is none like unto thee O Lord, whoſe Name is great in Might.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:33585:36"/>
Thy Name alone is excellent.</p>
               <p>The Lord is above all Gods, the only Potentate, King of Kings and Lord of Lords; the abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, who hath a boundleſs and infinite Supremacy.</p>
               <p>Thou deſerveſt to receive from every Underſtanding Nature Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ceaſing Praiſes, and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to be worſhipp'd with the moſt humble Proſtrations.</p>
               <p>Who is like unto thee, O Lord, among the Gods? Who is like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee among the Gods, glorious in Holineſs, fearful in Praiſes, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wonders?</p>
               <p>Thou ruleſt by thy power for ever, of old thou haſt laid the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the Earth. The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33585:37"/>
are the Works of thy Hands, they ſhall periſh but thou ſhalt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure; yea all of them ſhall wax old like a Garment; and as a Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture ſhalt thou change them; they ſhall be changed, but thou art the ſame, and thy years have no end.</p>
               <p>Thy Throne, O God, is for ever and ever; thy Kingdom is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Kingdom.</p>
               <p>O Lord thou art worthy of all Honour, Glory, and Power; for thou haſt created all things: and for thy pleaſure they are and were created.</p>
               <p>The glorious Productions of thine Omnipotency, they ſpeak thee to be infinitely Excellent. They are the Evidences and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of thy Infinite
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33585:37"/>
Wiſdom, Power, and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt garniſhed the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Works of thy Wiſdom, and art from everlaſting to everlaſting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Thy Works praiſe thee, and are honourable and glorious, and are to be had in remembrance to all generations.</p>
               <p>They are thy Witneſſes that thou art God.</p>
               <p>The Heavens declare thy Glory, and the Firmament ſheweth thy Handy-work.</p>
               <p>The Operations of thy Hands are Teſtimonies of thy Glory, Glaſſes of thy Beauty, Preachers of thy Wiſdom, and Provokers of Love.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:33585:38"/>
O Lord, how manifold are thy Works, in Wiſdom haſt thou made them.</p>
               <p>Thou formedſt the Earth by thy Power, eſtabliſhed the World by thy Wiſdom, and didſt ſpread forth the Heavens by thy Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>By thy Word thou didſt hang the Earth upon the Waters.</p>
               <p>Thou createſt all things, thou bringeſt out their Hoſt by number by the greatneſs of thy Might.</p>
               <p>Thou telleſt the number of the Stars, by thy Word they are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt appointed the Moon for Seaſons, and the Sun knoweth his going down.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:33585:38"/>
Thou haſt builded thy Stories in the Heavens, and founded thy Troops upon Earth.</p>
               <p>Thou doſt greater things than theſe are, for we have ſeen but a few of thy Works.</p>
               <p>Thou do'ſt great things, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable marvellous things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out number.</p>
               <p>With thee is Wiſdom and Strength, Counſel and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>The Conſideration of thy Works are Entertainments worthy of the beſt and moſt raiſed Minds.</p>
               <p>Honour and Majeſty are bfore thee, Strength and Beauty are in thy Sanctuary.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:33585:39"/>
Glory and Honour are in thy Preſence, Strength and Gladneſs are in thy Place.</p>
               <p>In thy preſence is fulneſs of Joy, and at thy right hand there are pleaſures for evermore.</p>
               <p>Thou humbleſt thy Self when thou beholdeſt the things that are done in Heaven and in Earth.</p>
               <p>Even as the Clay is in the hand of the Potter, ſo all the Nations of the Earth are at thy diſpoſal.</p>
               <p>The Kingdom is the Lords, thou art Governour among the Nations.</p>
               <p>Thou art great in Wiſdom and mighty in Power, and beholdeſt all things continually.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:33585:39"/>
Thou ſeeſt from everlaſting to everlaſting, there is nothing that is wonderful unto thee.</p>
               <p>The great Orderer and Diſpoſer of all Things.</p>
               <p>There is nothing ſo high that is above thy Providence, there is nothing ſo low that is beneath thy Providence.</p>
               <p>There is nothing ſo large but it is bounded by thy Providence, there is nothing ſo confuſed but thou canſt order it, there is nothing ſo contrived but thou canſt diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point it.</p>
               <p>Thou keepeſt every thing upon the right Wheel, for the managing of thy moſt righteous Affairs both in Heaven and Earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:33585:40"/>
Thou turneſt the way of the Wicked upſide down, the Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and the Deceived are thine.</p>
               <p>The Lord bringeth the Counſel of the Wicked to naught, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Devices of the People of none effect.</p>
               <p>Thou diſappointeſt the Devices of the Crafty, ſo that they cannot perform their Enterprize.</p>
               <p>Thou takeſt the Wiſe in their own Craftineſs, the Counſel of the Froward thou carry'ſt head-long.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt power of Life and Death, thou leadeſt down to the gates of Hell and bringeſt up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               <p>Before thee the Nations are but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33585:40"/>
as the Drop of a Bucket, or as the Small Duſt of the Ballance.</p>
               <p>Thou guideſt the Stars, thou thundereſt in the Clouds, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the hearts of Kings as Rivers of Water.</p>
               <p>Thou treadeſt upon the Circle of the Earth, and all the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants are but as Graſhoppers.</p>
               <p>Thou ſtretcheſt out the Heavens like a Curtain, and foldeſt them up as a Tent to dwell in.</p>
               <p>Thy Bleſſed Will the power of man is not able to with-ſtand, the Eternal Decrees no conſpiracy is able to impair.</p>
               <p>Thou increaſeſt the Nations, and deſtroyeſt them; thou enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33585:41"/>
the Nations, and ſtraitens them again.</p>
               <p>When thou ſtretcheſt out thy Hand who can reſtrain it.</p>
               <p>Thou weakeneſt the ſtrength of the mighty, thou powreſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon Princes.</p>
               <p>Thy Counſels ſtand ſure, thou doſt all thy Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>The Lord hath his way in the Whirlwind, the Storm and the Clouds are the Duſt of his Feet.</p>
               <p>Thou doſt whatſoever thou pleaſeſt both in Heaven and in Earth.</p>
               <p>Thy Will cannot go beyond thy Power, who can ſpeak the World into nothing.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:33585:41"/>
It's God that bringeth down the high, and exalteth the low.</p>
               <p>That drieth up the Green Tree, and that cauſeth the Dry Tree to flouriſh.</p>
               <p>God is Judg, he ſetteth up one and pulleth down another.</p>
               <p>Thou art the great Rewarder and Puniſher of Good and Evil.</p>
               <p>Thou filleſt Heaven and Earth with thy preſence.</p>
               <p>Thou art acquainted with all our ways, and pondereſt all our goings.</p>
               <p>Thou ſitteſt upon the Thrones in the Heavens, and from thence beholdeſt the bottomleſs places.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:33585:42"/>
There is not any Creature that is not manifeſt in thy ſight.</p>
               <p>All things are naked before thine Eyes with whom we have to do.</p>
               <p>He that planted the Ear ſhall he not hear, and he that formed the Eye ſhall he not ſee.</p>
               <p>Thou diſcovereſt Deep things out of Darkneſs, and bringeth to Light the Shadow of Death.</p>
               <p>Thou declareſt the things that are paſt and for to come, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealeth the ſteps of hidden things. No thought eſcapeth thee, neither is any word hidden from thee.</p>
               <p>The ways of good men and the goodneſs of their ways, and the ways of evil men, and the evil of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33585:42"/>
their ways, are not hidden from thee.</p>
               <p>The Lord is in his Holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Lords Throne is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, his Eyes behold, his Eye lids try the Children of Men.</p>
               <p>Thou ſearcheſt the Heart, thou trieſt the Reins, that thou may'ſt give unto every Man according to his ways, and according to the fruit of his doings.</p>
               <p>Thou watcheſt over the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to pluck them up and to deſtroy them; but thou watcheſt over the Righteous to build them and to plant.</p>
               <p>We own thy abſolute Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty over us, and although thou art girded with Strength, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33585:43"/>
who can ſay, What doeſt thou? Yet thou doeſt nothing but what is equal and right.</p>
               <p>Thy ways are always full of righteouſneſs, tho not always full of clearneſs to mortals.</p>
               <p>Thou art righteous in all thy Ways, and juſt in all thy Judgments.</p>
               <p>As thou art known to be King of Nations by thy works of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence abroad in the World, ſo thou art known to be the King of Saints, becauſe the Scepter of thy Kingdom is a Scepter of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</p>
               <p>Thou loveſt Righteouſneſs and Judgment, and takeſt pleaſure in Uprightneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:33585:43"/>
All the Works of the Lord are good, he giveth every one in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and when need is; ſo that a man need not ſay this is worſe than that, for in due time all thy doings will prove worthy of praiſe.</p>
               <p>Our God one day will bring forth all the grounds of all his Diſpenſations towards Man, and all the Proceedings with him, in ſuch a demonſtrative and undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Conſonancy, even to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Reaſon of Man, that every Mouth ſhall be ſtopped.</p>
               <p>Its far from thee to do wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, its far from the Almighty to commit iniquity.</p>
               <p>Thy Counſels of old are Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:33585:44"/>
Thou ſitteſt upon the Throne of Holineſs.</p>
               <p>To thee Cherubim and Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phim continually do cry, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy Lord God of Sabbaoth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Righteouſneſs and Judgment are the Habitations of thy Throne.</p>
               <p>Thou keepeſt the Paths of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>According to thy Name, O Lord, ſo are thy praiſes to the ends of the Earth; thy right hand is full of Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>Thou exerciſeſt Loving Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Righteouſneſs, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Earth, for thou excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:33585:44"/>
They that honour thee thou wilt honour, but they that deſpiſe thee, ſhall be but lightly eſteemed.</p>
               <p>The righteouſneſs of the Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right ſhall deliver them, but the Wicked ſhall be caught in their own naughtineſs.</p>
               <p>The Lord loveth the righteous, but the wicked and him that loveth violence, his Soul hateth.</p>
               <p>The Lord is known by the Judgment that he executeth, the wicked is ſnar'd in the work of his own hands.</p>
               <p>The fooliſh ſhall not ſtand in thy ſight, thou hateſt all the workers of iniquity.</p>
               <p>He that will not bow to thy
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33585:45"/>
Scepter of Mercy, ſhall be cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in pieces by the Rod of thy Wrath.</p>
               <p>With thee is terrible Majeſty.</p>
               <p>Thou canſt ſhew thy ſtrength at all times, and who may with-ſtand the power of thine Arm.</p>
               <p>At thy wrath the Earth ſhall tremble, the wicked ſhall not be able to abide thine Indignation.</p>
               <p>Thou who build'ſt the World, can'ſt eaſily deſtroy the wicked.</p>
               <p>Thou art wiſe in heart and mighty in ſtrength, who hath harden'd himſelf againſt thee and proſper'd.</p>
               <p>The Pillars of Heaven tremble and are aſtoniſh'd at thy reproof.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:33585:45"/>
Thro the greatneſs of thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhall thy enemies ſubmit unto thee.</p>
               <p>We adore thy righteouſneſs, O God, when thou puniſheſt the wicked, becauſe they trample up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy moſt righteous Edicts.</p>
               <p>When thou judgeſt, 'tis not out of Soveraignty but Juſtice.</p>
               <p>Thou never did'ſt command Man to do any thing, but what was conducible to his own happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Thou madeſt the World for Man, thou madeſt Man to obey thee; and the reaſon thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded'ſt Man to ſerve thee, was that thereby he might be eternally bleſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:33585:46"/>
If we had walk'd in thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, they had before this time led us out from under the Curſe we are now labouring under.</p>
               <p>One day in thy Courts is better than a thouſand elſewhere. It's better to be a Door-keeper in the Houſe of God than to dwell in the Tents of Wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>We taſte and reliſh the joys of Heaven, when we contemplate thy Attributes, which are the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications of thy Nature, ſo far as is knowable.</p>
               <p>The Demonſtrations that thou haſt given of thy ſelf in thy Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, is ſufficient, if we did but rightly conſider, to make us both fear and love thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:33585:46"/>
Thy Holineſs, Juſtice, and Power, well conſider'd, would put a Bridle in our Jaws, to keep us from ruſhing into Sin as a Horſe ruſheth into the Battle.</p>
               <p>And thy Mercy, Truth, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Sufficiency well learn'd, is enough to make us love thee, and to be a willing people in the day of thy Power.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:33585:47"/>
               <head>Confeſsion of Sin.</head>
               <p>OUR Guilt flaſheth in our Faces, wo unto us, for we have ſinned.</p>
               <p>We have not kept the way of the Lord, but perfidiouſly depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from our God.</p>
               <p>In the greatneſs of our Folly we have gone aſtray.</p>
               <p>We have Prophan'd our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are due onely to God, by ſetting them upon baſe and contemptible Objects.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:33585:47"/>
The Spirit of Fornication is in the midſt of us.</p>
               <p>According to the multitude of the Fruit we have increaſed the Altars, according to the goodneſs of our Land we have made the Images.</p>
               <p>We have gone a Whoring after our own Inventions.</p>
               <p>Sin like a ſtrong Byaſs, hath drawn our hearts from God.</p>
               <p>We have run after other Lovers, our Adulteries are between our Breaſts.</p>
               <p>We have tempted Temptation to deceive us.</p>
               <p>How hotly we have follow'd the Chaſe of our own Deluſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:33585:48"/>
We are guilty of the two Old Evils, we have ſnatch'd at the Shadow but let go the Subſtance: VVe have forſaken the Fountains of Living Water, and have hewn unto our ſelves broken Ciſterns that hold no VVater.</p>
               <p>Inſtead of truſting in God that giveth good things, we have truſted in the good things that God hath ſent.</p>
               <p>Inſtead of rejoycing in God that giveth us Bleſſings, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Bleſſings that God hath given.</p>
               <p>We have gaz'd upon the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but conſider'd not the britle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: We have look'd upon their glory, but forgot the frailty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:33585:48"/>
Wordly Luſts hath abuſed our Sight, and cozen'd our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>The Earth is thy Foot-ſtool, we have made it our Throne; Heaven is thy Throne, we have made it our Foot-ſtool.</p>
               <p>We have been for this World as tho it would never have an ending, and for the VVorld to come as tho it would never have beginning.</p>
               <p>Inſtead of laying up our Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Heaven, we have laid up our Heaven in our Treaſure.</p>
               <p>We have been groſs Idolaters, in paying Adorations to earthy things.</p>
               <p>We have pawn'd Heaven for a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33585:49"/>
few trifles, and given infinite of years purchaſe for them.</p>
               <p>We have taken our Egyptian Jewels, thoſe Temporal Bleſſings thou haſt ſo plentifully caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and have made a Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calf of them; adoring and truſting it, and have fallen off from the Cauſe of Cauſes.</p>
               <p>We have ſet up Idols in our Hearts that deſtroy our Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>The VViſe Man truſteth in his VViſdom, the Strong Man in his Strength, and the Rich Man in his Riches: Thus we have brought our ſelves under the Curſe, by truſting in the arm of Fleſh.</p>
               <p>The Ballances of Deceit are in our hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:33585:49"/>
We have wrought a deceitful Work.</p>
               <p>We have walk'd in a Fool's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, ſurveying the fading Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Imaginary Felicities, catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Apples of <hi>Sodom,</hi> that vaniſh away in Smoke.</p>
               <p>We have been ſerious about Trifles, and trifl'd about Serious Things.</p>
               <p>We have furied our ſelves in the purſuit of the fugitive Toys of this life, which if they were put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Ballance, would prove alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether lighter than Vanity.</p>
               <p>We have ſpent our Money for that which is not Bread, and our Labour for that which ſatisfieth not.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:33585:50"/>
We have wandr'd at random in the vaſt emptineſs of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>What we find moſt perfect in this World, is rather meerly Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and Imaginative, than Real and Subſtantial; the beſt Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Life, being but a Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Vanity.</p>
               <p>We have wildr'd our ſelves in our own Mazes, and wearied our ſelves with meer Vanity.</p>
               <p>We have ſold our ſelves for naught.</p>
               <p>With <hi>Eſau</hi> we have deſpiſed our Birth-right.</p>
               <p>With <hi>Cain</hi> we have gone out from the preſence of the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:33585:50"/>
With the Prodigal we have gone into a far Countrey.</p>
               <p>Every ſtep we have ſet forward in Sin, hath been a ſtep backward from thee.</p>
               <p>Our Habitation hath been in the midſt of Deceit, 'tis thro Deceit that we refuſe to know the Lord.</p>
               <p>We have drawn the Worlds two Breſts Profit and Pleaſure, and fallen aſleep at them, but have neglected the Things that concern our Everlaſting Peace.</p>
               <p>We have neither delighted in the Law of God, nor the God of the Law.</p>
               <p>The Thefts and Wiles of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity hath not only ſtoln us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33585:51"/>
from our ſelves but from God.</p>
               <p>Our Deſires and Affections have been journeying we know not where.</p>
               <p>We have cauſe to be aſhamed becauſe of the Oaks that we deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the Gardens that we have choſen.</p>
               <p>We have truſted unanchor'd Hope in fleeting Streams.</p>
               <p>We have pitch'd our thoughts and the reſtleſs deſires of our Souls upon the Creature, as tho there were nothing beyond the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>We have ſtretched out our wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd Arms beyond their Dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33585:51"/>
and our Hands have graſp'd beyond their Diſtance, to incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs this inferiour Orb, but we are forc'd to come off, not only with Vanity of Vanities but with Vexation of Spirit.</p>
               <p>We have ſought the Living among the Dead, Happineſs where 'tis not to be found.</p>
               <p>We have ſought Strength in Weakneſs, Riches in Poverty, Gloryin Shame, and Life in Death; and in this courſe we have forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our own Mercy.</p>
               <p>We find by woful experience that all Wordly Enjoyments ſtand upon two lame Legs, Inſufficiency, Uncertainty.</p>
               <p>The end of all our Earthly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33585:52"/>
eateth up the pleaſure we had in them, like <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s lean Kine.</p>
               <p>We have ſown the VVind to reap the VVhirl-wind.</p>
               <p>The Magnetic Power of the VVorld hath drawn our Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances downward, which thou madeſt erect for the Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Thee and thy VVorks; but now the Curſe of the Serpent is upon us, upon our Bellies do we creep, and Duſt do we eat all the days of our lives.</p>
               <p>We are deeply ſunk in the VVorlds Quickſands.</p>
               <p>The Earth hath ſwallow'd us up alive.</p>
               <p>Our Affections the Feet of our
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33585:52"/>
Souls, have ſtuck faſt in the mire and clay of the VVorld, ſo that we have been hindred from running the race that hath been ſet before us.</p>
               <p>We have wearied our ſelves in the way of VVickedneſs, but the way of Truth we have not known.</p>
               <p>The bewitching of VVordly tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles have obſcured and hid from us the good things.</p>
               <p>We have rather choſen to go aſtray, than to walk in the ſweet Rules of thy Commands.</p>
               <p>Our Reſt and our Luſts have ſhared our Time.</p>
               <p>VVe are ſtrangers to the life of Grace thro the Ignorance that is in us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:33585:53"/>
We have taken bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter: What Poiſon or Gall ſo bitter as Sin? Yet we have delighted our ſelves therein. VVhat more ſweet than thy Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony? More to be deſired than gold, yea than much fine gold; ſweeter alſo then the honey and the honey-comb, yet we nauſeated them.</p>
               <p>Damn'd Satan with his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phean Aires and dexterous VVar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, with Maſques and Triumphs hath inticed us along in the paths of Death.</p>
               <p>Sin hath betray'd us with a Kiſs.</p>
               <p>Pleaſure merrieth our Senſes for a while, but Horror followeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and vultereth our unconſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:33585:53"/>
Sin is ſweet in the commiſſion, but bitter in the recollection, in the Mouth 'tis as ſweet as honey, but in the Belly as bitter as gall.</p>
               <p>Sinful Pleaſures have been the Thieves that have train'd us out of the way and robb'd us.</p>
               <p>With <hi>Ahab</hi> we have ſold our ſelves to work wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>We have made haſt in the paths of Death.</p>
               <p>We have not onely woven the Spider's Web, but we have hatch'd the Cockatrice Egg.</p>
               <p>Our Actions have not onely been vain and unprofitable, but dangerous.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:33585:54"/>
We have not onely not been for thee, but againſt thee.</p>
               <p>We have not onely not gathered, but ſcattered.</p>
               <p>We have deſp'rately invaded the moſt equal Rules of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
               <p>We have broken thy Bonds in ſunder, and caſt away thy Cords from us.</p>
               <p>We have laid the Reins of our Loyalty upon the Neck of Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Liberty.</p>
               <p>We have proceeded from Evil to Evil, not conſidering thy Purity and Juſtice.</p>
               <p>We have drawn Iniquity with the Cords of Vanity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:33585:54"/>
Every thought and imagination of our hearts have been evil, and that continually.</p>
               <p>The frame of our hearts have not onely been evil continually, but our hearts have framed that which hath been evil continually.</p>
               <p>Altho thou hateſt iniquity with a perfect hatred, yet even as a Fountain caſteth forth her water, ſo have we caſt out our iniquities before thee.</p>
               <p>Heaven and Earth teſtifie againſt us that thou as an indulgent Father haſt brought us up as dear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but we have rebell'd againſt thee.</p>
               <p>We have be-leaper'd our ſelves with Sin, and like drunken men
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33585:55"/>
have ſtagger'd in our own vomit.</p>
               <p>VVe have wrought abbomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before thee.</p>
               <p>As a Mill-wheel is continually turn'd round, and ever drench'd with a new ſtream: ſo are we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually hurried with the Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our various Sins.</p>
               <p>We have progreſs'd in the ways of Vice, and ſpacious fields of dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Luxury, and have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in nothing but perpetual of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending.</p>
               <p>We have offered violence to thy patience and long-ſuffering, extorting ſeverities from thee, by the audacious Importunities of our Notorious Impieties; as tho we would wreſtle a Fall or fight a Duel
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33585:55"/>
with the Almighty: We have run upon him, even upon his Neck, upon the thick Boſſes of his Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</p>
               <p>We have plow'd iniquity and ſow'd wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>We have continually lived in contempt of thy Majeſty, and tranſgreſſion of thy Commands.</p>
               <p>We have ſtream'd out our days in Riot and Exceſs.</p>
               <p>We have revell'd in a Shoreleſs Exceſs, in the ungirth'd Solaces of Senſual Liberty.</p>
               <p>Our longing for the Forbidden Fruit, ſheweth us all to be the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Eve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:33585:56"/>
Oh how abominable and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy is Man, that drinketh up ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity like water.</p>
               <p>VVe have laid our hearts in Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Pleaſures, forgetting what will be in the end thereof.</p>
               <p>VVe have ſwum down the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizing Torrent of theſe laſt and lewdeſt days, againſt the ſecret Waſts and Counter-blaſts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming Conſciences.</p>
               <p>We have gone in the common track, and waved with the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton train of the VVorld.</p>
               <p>Our Judgments have been bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to miſapprehenſion, and we ſeduced to bad actions.</p>
               <p>VVe have given to our will the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33585:56"/>
reins, and have yielded to all that Senſe requires.</p>
               <p>VVe have hood-wink'd our Souls with preſumption.</p>
               <p>Sin and Sin hath gone hand in hand, and blood hath touched blood.</p>
               <p>Opportunity and our Nature, like two inordinate Lovers, they ſeldom meet, but they ſin toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>We have run careleſly in Sin, not being aware of the Stabbing Shams that await us in a Killing Ambuſh; our own purblind ſight leaving them undiſcovered.</p>
               <p>Charming pleaſures ſing us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Lethargies, while Damnation
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33585:57"/>
ſtealeth inſenſibly upon us: they dandle us into Flames.</p>
               <p>We have confronted thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Kindneſs with unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Unworthineſs.</p>
               <p>Atheiſm hath poſſeſſed our Hearts, and luxurious Lewdneſs hath polluted our Bodies.</p>
               <p>We have bathed our ſelves in the muddy Streams of Luxury and Riot.</p>
               <p>Altho we have known the way of the Lord and the Judgments of our God, yet we have altogether broken the Yoke and burſt the Bands.</p>
               <p>Our Impieties are of the largeſt Dimenſions, we have taken pains
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33585:57"/>
to make our ſelves the heirs of Darkneſs.</p>
               <p>We have prodigally contributed to our own ruin.</p>
               <p>We have been as active in work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out our Damnation, as we ſhould have been to work out our Salvation.</p>
               <p>Inſtead of arming our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the day of wrath, we have armed the day of wrath againſt our ſelves.</p>
               <p>The Oil of Mercy hath made us more active in the feats of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety.</p>
               <p>VVe have look'd upon all thy favours thro the contracting Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks of Ingratitude.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:33585:58"/>
The freſh and green Paſtures have made us fat and proud, and with <hi>Jeſurun</hi> ſpurn againſt our God.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt filled our Cup, but thro careleſneſs and an uneven hand we have ſpill'd moſt of it.</p>
               <p>It's a wonder thou haſt not ſhrunk thy deſcending favours.</p>
               <p>We have fought againſt God with his own weapons: If thou hadſt not been ſo kind to us, we could not have been ſo unkind to thee.</p>
               <p>The warmth of Proſperity hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up Luxury.</p>
               <p>We are the Wonders and Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles of Unthankfulneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:33585:58"/>
The worldly Bleſſings thou haſt ſo plentifully beſtow'd upon us, have been the cauſes of our Pride, Riot, Tyranny, and Exceſs.</p>
               <p>It's pity that fair weather ſhould do any harm.</p>
               <p>Our Halcyonian days, our Health, our Peace, our Liberty, our Plenty, hath brought forth Spiders and Caterpillers; Pride and Prophaneneſs: therefore we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God to ſend ſhowers of wrath to cleanſe them away.</p>
               <p>The cry of our Sins hath inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Heaven.</p>
               <p>Our Impieties ſtare Heaven and Earth in the face, and beat the Air for Vengeance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:33585:59"/>
Our Sins have ripen'd us for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               <p>From the Crown of the Head to the Sole of the Foot, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but bruiſes and wounds and putrifying Sores.</p>
               <p>Our Eyes being full of Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, our Tongues being unruly Evils, full of deadly Poiſon, our Throats open Sepulchres, our Hearts deceitful above meaſure, and deſp'rately wicked; the Dens and Caves of Uncleanneſs: Our Hands full of Miſchief, our Feet ready in the Paths of the Deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Yea, all our Members are the Inſtruments of Unrighteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>We have every day rais'd Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents to our own Shame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:33585:59"/>
If the Beaſts could ſpeak, they might ſay that Really that God ſpake once Ironically, Man is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as one of us: yea like all of us. For we have of the Fox, the VVolf, the Tyger, the Swine, and the Dog, yea ſome of the evil of every Beaſt.</p>
               <p>Our wickedneſs is condemn'd by its own witneſs.</p>
               <p>Our Sins teſtifie againſt us.</p>
               <p>The guilt of our own miſguid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Souls condemn us.</p>
               <p>We have brambl'd our way to Vertue.</p>
               <p>We have ſpun Cords of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity out of our own bowels, and Satan bound us with them; ſo that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33585:60"/>
now we are under the Chains of an habituated courſe of Sin, and except God help, thoſe Chains will reſerve us unto everlaſting Chains.</p>
               <p>We have fitted our ſelves for wrath, and are the Procurers and Artificers of our own ruin.</p>
               <p>We have incloſed our ſelves in a Den of Thraldoms.</p>
               <p>We have laid wait for our own Blood, and lurked privily for our own Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>VVe have deſtin'd our ſelves to miſery.</p>
               <p>VVe have poſted with precipitant and winged haſte towards our own deſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:33585:60"/>
Like Rivers we have run haſtily to loſe our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Atheiſm and Infidelity hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched us with a deſperate ſenſleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>VVe are Children of Infidelity.</p>
               <p>Our hearts have been the Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Unbelief.</p>
               <p>Our Incredulity have eclipſed Gods Sufficiency.</p>
               <p>Wiſdom hath cry'd and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hath lift up her Voice.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt ſet before us Life and Death, Bleſſing and Curſing. Yet we have been like deaf Adders, not hearkening to the Voice of the Charmer charm he never ſo wiſely.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:33585:61"/>
We have ſhut the Windows of our Souls againſt the Light of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>The Foxes have holes, the Birds of the Air have Neſts, but the Son of Man hath not where to lay his Head.</p>
               <p>We have room enough for crafty and ſubtil Inventions and Contrivances, and high and ſoar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Thoughts, but the Lord Chriſt is kept out.</p>
               <p>We have hated Knowledg, we have contemned thy Counſels and deſpiſed thy Reproofs.</p>
               <p>A Frozen Stupidity hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num'd us, Plainneſs hath not made us underſtand.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:33585:61"/>
Serious piercing Warnings have not made us afraid, the greateſt matters wrought upon us, the ſweeteſt things have not enticed us, the moſt dreadful things have not terrified us, Truth and Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity have not convinced us. The God that made us, the Chriſt that redeem'd us, the Holy Ghoſt that would ſanctifie us, prevail not with us.</p>
               <p>Our Diſobedience is rooted in Folly and Ingratitude.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt purſued us with Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and follow'd us with cloſe Convictions, yet we are Pilgrims and Strangers in the Knowledg of God.</p>
               <p>We have ſtopp'd the Organs of our Mind with Earthy Oppilations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:33585:62"/>
We have broke a thouſand Bonds that ſhould have kept us to our Duty.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt given us the means of Grace, thy Word, thy Meſſengers, our Conſciences: Threatnings from Mount <hi>Ebal</hi> to ſtop us in our Career of Sin, Promiſes from Mount <hi>Gerizzim</hi> to allure us into the paths of life. The Examples of Holy Men to guide us, that we may follow the Foot-ſteps of the Flock, and thy Holy Spirit attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon theſe and many other Aſſiſtances in our Courſe to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: but we hate to be reform'd, and make all our Returns in Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
               <p>Altho thou haſt made out unto us thy Wiſdom, Holineſs, Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Goodneſs, Mercy and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33585:62"/>
Long Suffering, Power and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. And altho thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed Free Grace unto all thoſe that are a willing People in the day of thy Power, but Tribulation and Wrath unto the Diſobedient. And notwithſtanding the Divine Authority, that unlimited Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy that thou haſt over us; and notwithſtanding the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy Scepter, yet we have ſo degenerated from Reaſon and apoſtatized from all Ingenuity, that we have not kept the way of the Lord, but wickedly departed from our God.</p>
               <p>We are like to the Wild Aſs that ſnuffeth up the VVind at her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in her occaſion who can turn her away. In the height of our Proſperity we ſay with <hi>Pharaoh; Who is the Lord that I ſhould obey</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:33585:63"/>
                  <hi>his voice?</hi> but in her Month they'll find her. So Extremities and Death-Bed Pangs will ſeize us, the time is coming, that we muſt fall into the hands of the Living God.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt given us ſpace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, but we have not found the place of Repentance.</p>
               <p>We have had line upon line<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> precept upon precept.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt hearken'd and heard no man ſpeak aright, ſaying, What have I done? Every one turn'd to his courſe, as the Horſe ruſheth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Battle, careleſly, fearleſly and deſperately; the Stork of the Heavens knoweth her appointed time, the Turtle, the Swallow and the Crane know the time of their coming; but we have not
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33585:63"/>
known the Judgments of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Irrational Creatures know by inſtinct of Nature to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void ſuch intemperate Weather as would be deſtructive to them, yet we, notwithſtanding many Warnings, have not flown from the wrath to come.</p>
               <p>We have wreſtled with thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and urged thee to ſwear in thy wrath, that we ſhall never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into thy reſt.</p>
               <p>Well may we be compared to Children ſitting in the Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, calling one unto another and ſaying, <hi>We have piped unto ye but ye have not danced; we have mourn'd unto ye, but ye have not wept.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:33585:64"/>
We have been inflexible to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Threatnings.</p>
               <p>Neither th'acute Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Terror, not the Ponderous Inductions of Intereſt, have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with us.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt many times beat up for Voluntiers amongſt us, and haſt proclaimed the Priviledges, Prerogatives, Graces and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts that belong to thy Followers, but we have turned our backs.</p>
               <p>And thou haſt warn'd us to flee from the wrath to come, yet we have come in the very face of that wrath which thou haſt warn'd us to flee.</p>
               <p>The Trumpets have ſounded, and the Lions have roared upon
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33585:64"/>
us, and yet we have hardened our hearts.</p>
               <p>We have made thee to ſerve with our ſins, as tho thou wert bound to indure our abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>We have offered Violence to thy Law, and have made ſuch large Breaches in our Duty, as tho thou wert forc'd to abide our Contempt.</p>
               <p>We have been Profeſſors of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, but Practiſers of Iniquity.</p>
               <p>How little have we advanced in Religion?</p>
               <p>The Faith of Chriſtians have been in our Mouths, but the works of Infidels in our Hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:33585:65"/>
We have been meer Promiſers of Obedience.</p>
               <p>We have betray'd our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus with a Kiſs.</p>
               <p>Our Actions Religious have been meerly Theatrical, and done in Subornation to ſome other Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</p>
               <p>Our Goodneſs is but like the Morning Dew.</p>
               <p>VVe have delighted more in the Theatre than in the Cloſet.</p>
               <p>VVe have often bound our ſelves unto thee, but we have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited our Indentures.</p>
               <p>That which we have verbally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted we have actually embraced.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:33585:65"/>
We have look'd Heaven-ward in our Profeſſion, but Hell-ward in our Converſation.</p>
               <p>VVe have covenanted againſt Sin, yet we have ſin'd againſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
               <p>We have been rather Superfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al than Fundamental Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>The Heathen give real honour to counterfeit gods, but we give a counterfeit honour to the true God.</p>
               <p>Our Devotion to God our Love to our Brethren, 'tis a Meaſuring Caſt, hard to determine which is the Colder, but both ready to faint and fall down dead.</p>
               <p>We have put on the Sheep's Coat upon the Wolfs Back; the Velvet
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33585:66"/>
Plaiſter of Profeſſion upon the Stinking Ulcer of Corruption.</p>
               <p>Our Righteouſneſs is ſo imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that it can claim no Bleſſing; and our Wickedneſs ſo great, that it deſerves nothing but Curſing.</p>
               <p>We have the Spots and Tokens of the Plague of Plagues; we ſin and ſee it not, therefore neither care nor fear, nor repent nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend.</p>
               <p>Our Spot is not the Spot of thy People.</p>
               <p>We have hired thy Plagues as <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> did the King of <hi>Aſſur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Sins are envenomed with many hainous and helliſh Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: We deſpiſe thy Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33585:66"/>
we break righteous Laws, we contemn precious Promiſes, we give more credence to Satanical ſuggeſtions, than we do to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Word of God. We weave the VVeb of our own Woe, and ſpin the Cords of our own Thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and every Sin breaketh the Sacred Covenant between Chriſt and our ſouls.</p>
               <p>Thou mayſt juſtly pronounce <hi>Lo-ruhamah</hi> againſt us.</p>
               <p>We have been Traitors to our own Peace.</p>
               <p>We have daily multipli'd our own Calamities.</p>
               <p>Our own Inventions have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twined us and bewray'd us into many troubles, and incloſed us in a Den of Thraldoms.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:33585:67"/>
We day by day alarm Divine Juſtice.</p>
               <p>We have cauſe to fear there are many in Hell curſing our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</p>
               <p>We know not how many we have infected with the plague that is upon us.</p>
               <p>If thou ſhould'ſt lay Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Line and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Plumb-line, thou mayſt righteouſly make thy Wrath to ſmoke againſt us.</p>
               <p>We have provoked thee to feed us with Wormwood, and to give us Gall to drink.</p>
               <p>Our Sins have laid us moſt naked to thy Wrath.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:33585:67"/>
We have ripen'd our ſelves for Vengeance.</p>
               <p>Its unſpeakable forbearance, that thy fury is not kindl'd and broke out into a Flame againſt us.</p>
               <p>That the Water-flood hath not over-flown us, that the Deep hath not ſwallow'd us up, that the Pit hath not ſhut her mouth upon us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:33585:68"/>
               <head>GRAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LATION.</head>
               <p>LEt our never ceaſing Praiſes wait upon thee our God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thy wrath is not kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dl'd and broke out into a Flame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us.</p>
               <p>We are the Living Monuments of thy Mercy.</p>
               <p>Thy Patience ſuſpendeth Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>If thou ſhouldſt with-draw thy Patience and Long-ſuffering, we ſhould drop into Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:33585:68"/>
Its unſpeakable Mercy that we are not invelopp'd in the revenging Flames of Hell.</p>
               <p>Altho thou haſt not look'd upon our Sins approvingly yet patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>If thou hadſt but the Patience of Men and Angels, we ſhould ſpend it one day, thou couldſt not hold thy tongue and hands one hour.</p>
               <p>The life of our Souls is wrapp'd up in the life of Grace.</p>
               <p>All Sacrifice is too little for a ſweet ſavour, all Fatneſs is too little for a Burn'd Offering.</p>
               <p>How low ſhould we fall in ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thy Grace, and how high
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33585:69"/>
ſhould we riſe in Thankful Praiſes?</p>
               <p>Its great Condeſcenſion in thee to be content to be prais'd or belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by ſuch miſerable Creatures of uncircumciſed hearts and lips.</p>
               <p>Eternity it ſelf is little enough to praiſe thee.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed be the Majeſty of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for our Creation, and that we are Men and not Beaſts.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed be God for our Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Souls that are capable of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with thy own ſelf for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>Let our never-ceaſing Praiſes wait upon thee for our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the great Work which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels deſire to look into.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:33585:69"/>
Everlaſtingly praiſed be our God for the light of his Glory that ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt, to the praiſe and glory of his Grace.</p>
               <p>Our Praiſes wait upon thee, for Free Grace that unlimited Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of the higheſt Love and Bounty.</p>
               <p>Thy precious Love is from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to Eternity.</p>
               <p>That hath prevented the Lion from coming out of the Thicket, and hath kept the Deſtroyer out of ſight.</p>
               <p>That hath ſtopp'd the Mouths of the Lyons of thy Judgments, ſo as they have not torn in pieces, when there was none to deliver us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:33585:70"/>
Our Praiſes wait upon our God for Free Grace, that Bleſſed Root out of which ſpringeth all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and precious Myſteries of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>The moſt Beautiful Womb out of which Chriſt Jeſus with all his Heavenly Treaſures, the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Priviledges, Prerogatives, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Comforts that are to be had in him and by him, do come forth.</p>
               <p>The Bleſſed Cauſe that is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to produce the Bleſſed Effects of the Salvation of our Souls thro Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>The Bleſſed Fountain that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſends forth Streams of Comfort, to refreſh the dejected, diſconſolate, weary, and heavy loaden ones.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:33585:70"/>
The Bow thou haſt ſet in the Clouds of Spiritual Sorrow, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Contrite Ones that thy Wrath ſhall not over-flow them.</p>
               <p>Were it not for thy Grace, what ſhould we do when our Sins teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie againſt us, but call for the Mountains to fall upon us, and the Hills to cover us from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Thy Grace hath kept many Thouſands from following <hi>Judas</hi> into Deſpair.</p>
               <p>When we know not what to do then we turn our Eyes towards thee, and find there is yet hope for <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was Free Grace that our great Lord Chriſt lived and died to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:33585:71"/>
We adore the great Miniſter of Grace <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord, the Ark that ſaveth us from periſhing in the Floods of our Iniquities.</p>
               <p>Who was given for us, who was conceived and born for us, who lived and died for us, who roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for us, and who ever liveth and maketh Interceſſion for us.</p>
               <p>Who trod the Wine-Preſs alone.</p>
               <p>The Son of God became the Son of Man, that the Sons of Men might become the Sons of God.</p>
               <p>Who was made like unto all, that all might be made like unto him.</p>
               <p>Who ſought us in ſharp ways and bought us with a dear price.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:33585:71"/>
Who came from Heaven to Earth, that we may go from Earth to Heaven.</p>
               <p>The Brightneſs of the Fathers Glory, and the Expreſs Image of Perſon, paid the Price of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, to diſcharge us Rebels who were in our Filthineſs in our Blood.</p>
               <p>Our Jeſus leap'd into a Sea of Wrath to ſave us from periſhing.</p>
               <p>He waded thro a Sea of Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to procure a Pardon for our Tranſgreſſions.</p>
               <p>Who made himſelf Sin for us who knew no Sin, that we might be made the Righteouſneſs of God in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:33585:72"/>
He ſuffer'd our Croſs, that we might wear his Crown.</p>
               <p>He died our Death, that we might live his Life.</p>
               <p>Who endured our Hell that we might enjoy his Heaven.</p>
               <p>He bore our Griefs and carry'd our Sorrows.</p>
               <p>He was wounded for our Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions and bruiſed for our Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</p>
               <p>The Chaſtiſement<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of our Peace was upon him, and by his Stripes we may be healed.</p>
               <p>We all like Sheep have gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, but on him was laid the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of us all.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:33585:72"/>
Adored be Chriſt Jeſus, who hath done what we ought to have done, and ſuffered what we ought to have ſuffered.</p>
               <p>This is the ſolid Baſis of our Comfort.</p>
               <p>The Lord of Life is the Way to eſcape Eternal Death.</p>
               <p>Altho we have turn'd our Backs on Grace, and with the Iſraelites loath'd the Manna, and hath ſo little regarded what the Lord Chriſt hath done and ſuffer'd for us, and that Bleſſed Treaſure that he at ſo dear a rate bought for us, and hath been daily offer'd unto us, yet he pleadeth for us, ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth Judgment, and ſtayeth Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Vengeance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:33585:73"/>
Altho the Earth was thought too good for him, he thinketh not Heaven too good for us.</p>
               <p>Our Praiſes wait upon the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of Heaven for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Goſpel, the Wiſdom of God, ordained before the World unto our Glory, the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God unto Salvation, unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that believe. That migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Efflux and Emanation of Life and Spirit, freely iſſuing from an Omnipotent Source of Grace and Love: That true God-like Vital Influence whereby Divinity de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives it ſelf into the Souls of Men, inlivening and transforming them into its own likeneſs, and ſtrongly imprinting upon them a Copy of its own Beauty and Goodneſs.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed be God that thy Precepts
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:33585:73"/>
are yet our Heritage, in the Houſe of our Pilgrimage.</p>
               <p>The Light, without which the whole World would be but a dark Chaos.</p>
               <p>Our Praiſes wait upon our God, becauſe we are within the ſound of his Trumpets.</p>
               <p>Becauſe the Sun of the Goſpel ſhineth upon the Lot of our Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</p>
               <p>Our Praiſes wait upon thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Holy Spirit is ſtill ready to bear witneſs to our Spirits the Truth of thy Holy Word, which tranſcribeth thy Heart and Mind unto us.</p>
               <p>Thy Judgments thou haſt laid
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33585:74"/>
before us, and the Way of Truth, whereby we may be kept from the Paths of the Deſtroyer.</p>
               <p>Our Praiſes wait upon thee our God for all the faithful Diſpencers of thy Word and Sacraments.</p>
               <p>Its great favour that thou haſt not removed them into Corners, and that their Tongues do not cleave to the roofs of their Mouths.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jonah</hi> was ſent from <hi>Samaria</hi> to <hi>Nineveh,</hi> doubtleſs we have turn'd as deaf an Ear as ever did <hi>Samaria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Its unſpeakable Mercy that thou haſt not commanded the Clouds that they rain no more rain upon us.</p>
               <p>That thou haſt not pronounced
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:33585:74"/>
againſt us, <hi>They that are filthy let them be filthy still, and they that are unrighteous, let them be unrighteous ſtill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Praiſes wait upon our God for all the great and precious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, ratified by the Oath of God the Father, ſealed by the Blood of God the Son, teſtified by God the Holy Ghoſt; and deliver'd by the hand of Mercy.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Breathings of Divine Love.</p>
               <p>The Breaſts of the Goſpel, out of which we draw forth ſo much Conſolation.</p>
               <p>Thoſe firm Foundations to build upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:33585:75"/>
Great and precious Promiſes.</p>
               <p>To the Chief of Sinners.</p>
               <p>To them that have been prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galizing all their days, and ſpent all upon Luſt.</p>
               <p>To them that have all the day been ſtanding idle in the Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, even until the Eleventh hour.</p>
               <p>Altho we have run ſo much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſcore, that if thou ſhouldſt arreſt us, all the Angels of Heaven could not bail us, yet whoever cometh unto thee, thou wilt in no wiſe caſt off.</p>
               <p>Tho our Sins be as Crimſon, thou wilt make them as Snow; and tho they be as Scarlet, thou wilt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33585:75"/>
make them as Wooll, if we are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and obedient.</p>
               <p>If we confeſs and forſake our ſins, we ſhall find Mercy.</p>
               <p>The Bruiſed Reed thou wilt not break, the ſmoaking Flax thou wilt not quench.</p>
               <p>Thou deſpiſeſt not the deſires of a Contrite Heart.</p>
               <p>Our Sins ſhall be blotted out, when the times of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed be God for our Seaſons of Grace and Times of Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
               <p>That the Door of Hope ſtandeth
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33585:76"/>
yet open in the Valley of <hi>Achor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Lord is yet to be found, and that we have a time to ſeek him.</p>
               <p>And as we praiſe our God for the Springs above, ſo we praiſe thee for our Springs below; our Health, Wealth, Peace, and Liberty, with many other Bleſſings of this Life.</p>
               <p>We humbly and thankfully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, That we are capable of ſo much Mercy and Favour on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thro the Merits and Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>That Name is above every name in which we hide our ſelves.</p>
               <p>He ever liveth to make Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:33585:76"/>
Now when we look towards the Place where thine honour dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, towards thy Holy Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that we hope our Lord will not ſuffer us to receive Denial, or to come off without Favour and Grace.</p>
               <p>Let us be in thy Sight as they that find Favour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:33585:77"/>
               <head>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PPLICATION.</head>
               <p>GIve ear unto our Prayers, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend unto the voice of our Supplications.</p>
               <p>Suffer not the Sun of Mercy to ſet, leſt the dark Night of Wrath over take us.</p>
               <p>Give us not only Sparing Mercy but Saving Mercy.</p>
               <p>Give us not only ſpace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, but grace to repent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:33585:77"/>
In regard the Sun of Mercy ſhineth ſo warm upon us, cauſe the fruits of Grace to grow in us.</p>
               <p>Cauſe thy Rich Attracts to gain the Obedience of our Hearts.</p>
               <p>Bind us to the Good behaviour with the Bands of thy Love, that they may charm our Evil Spirits.</p>
               <p>Shed abroad thy Love in our Hearts, that Love may beget Love; that thy unſpeakable Love unto us may beget in us ſome Love unto thee.</p>
               <p>Faſten thy Goodneſs ſo upon us, that it may lead us to Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
               <p>That we may not only be thankful for Mercy, but fruitful under Mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:33585:78"/>
Fill us with the Apprehenſion of thy Goodneſs, that the Sun of Divine Favour, may be as the Manna that lieth on the top of all our outward Bleſſings, that our Souls may feed upon it.</p>
               <p>That the glorious Productions of thine Omnipotency may charm our Hearts to Reflect on the Cauſe of Cauſes and the Being of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p>God forbid that we ſhould any longer ſuck poiſon out of the ſweet Flowers of thy Mercy and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>The Spider gathers Poiſon out of the ſame Flower where the Bee gathers Honey.</p>
               <p>Becauſe Judgment is not execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33585:78"/>
ſpeedily, therefore the Hearts of the Children of Men are whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet in them to do Evil.</p>
               <p>But Long-ſuffering leadeth the Children of God to Repentance.</p>
               <p>The ſame Heat that ſoftens Wax hardeneth Dirt.</p>
               <p>We are depraved and baſe by Degeneration, make us worthy by Regeneration.</p>
               <p>We were ſhapen in Iniquity, and in Sin did our Mothers conceive us.</p>
               <p>The Root in which we were conceived and born; hath put forth innumerable of Branches; they are ſpread forth into many Actual Tranſgreſſions. We are
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:33585:79"/>
conceived, born, brought up, and grown to full Stature in Sin; ſo that now we are under the Chains of an habituated Courſe of Sin, and without help from Heaven, thoſe Chains will reſerve us to Eternal Chains.</p>
               <p>O Lord break theſe Bonds in ſunder, and caſt away theſe Cords from us.</p>
               <p>Separate Sin which thou ſo much hateſt from the Souls thou ſo much loveſt.</p>
               <p>Separate Sin from us, elſe it will ſeparate us from thee.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Law of the Spirit of Life that is in Chriſt Jeſus, to free us from the Law of Sin and Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:33585:79"/>
Deliver us from the Tyrannical Power of Sin, that we may turn unto thee from whom we have deeply revolted.</p>
               <p>Waſh away our Filth and purge our Blood by the Spirit of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the Spirit of Burning.</p>
               <p>Thou who takeſt away the Sins of the World, take away the World of our Sins.</p>
               <p>Caſt out the Bond-woman and her Seed.</p>
               <p>Subdue our unruly Inclinations to do Evil.</p>
               <p>Bridle our Unreſtrained, Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and Diſtempered Paſſions.</p>
               <p>Caſhier the Turbulent Rout of our Corrupt Affections.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:33585:80"/>
We have cauſe with the Men of <hi>Jericho</hi> to complain of our Stinking Waters, throw in Salt to heal them.</p>
               <p>Sin is never kindlily caſt out, but by the Introduction of Grace.</p>
               <p>Sin reigneth, cauſe Grace to ſtep in and exauctorate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne it.</p>
               <p>Deſtroy the Weakneſs and the Moth, cauſe our Corruptions to flee into Hell, ever to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſeal up the root of Evil.</p>
               <p>We want a Touch of the Lord to heal our Bloody Iſſues.</p>
               <p>Shut up the Womb and dry up the Breaſts of Sin.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:33585:80"/>
Melt down our Luſts, and cauſe them to wither at the Root.</p>
               <p>Thou madeſt Man upright, but he hath found out many Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Create in us New Hearts, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new right Spirits within us.</p>
               <p>Frame our Hearts fit for thy own purpoſe, that we may will and do according to thy own good pleaſure.</p>
               <p>We have all been Examples of Sin, make us all Examples of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
               <p>That Old Things may paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and all Things may become New.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:33585:81"/>
Vaſſallize our Rebellious Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Our Iniquities ſwallow us up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live.</p>
               <p>O break the Bars of Death, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer the Powers of Darkneſs, lead Captivity Captive.</p>
               <p>Deliver us from Sin that great Murderer that let Death into rhe World.</p>
               <p>It bringeth innumerable of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils to incompaſs us.</p>
               <p>It keepeth us faſt bound in the dreadful Expectation of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of thy inſupportable Wrath and fiery Indignation, who art a Sin hating and Sin avenging God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:33585:81"/>
Suffer not the God of this World to blind our Eyes, but give us a perfect ſight of Sin, as it is the deadly Enemy of our Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Peace.</p>
               <p>That we may hate Sin more than ever we loved it.</p>
               <p>That we may not only diſlike Sin, but that our diſlike may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and ſwell into a hatred of Sin.</p>
               <p>That we may not only loath Sin, but leave Sin.</p>
               <p>That we may ſly from Sin, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho robed in Succeſſes and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs.</p>
               <p>That we may not only fall out with Sin, but fall off from Sin.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:33585:82"/>
Secure us from the pernicious Effects of the Devils Malice, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him not to add poiſon to our Luſts, nor paint to the Objects.</p>
               <p>Suffer us not to be carried away by the heady Stream of any baſe Affection.</p>
               <p>Strengthen us, that when we meet with temptations, we may quit our ſelves like Men, and be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of thy Might.</p>
               <p>Put on thy Armour upon us, that we may be able to ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Wiles of the Devil.</p>
               <p>That our Loins may be girt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with Truth, and having on the Breaſt-plate of Righteouſneſs, and our Feet ſhod with the Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33585:82"/>
of the Goſpel of Peace, and the Shield of Faith to quench the Fiery Darts of the Wicked with the Helmet of Salvation, and the Sword of the Spirit in the Inner Man, then we ſhall be more than Conquerors.</p>
               <p>One Deep calleth to another, the depth of our Weakneſs to the depth of thy Strength, the depth of our Folly to the depth of thy Wiſdom; the depth of our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty to the depth of thy Riches, the depth of our Miſeries to the depth of thy Mercies.</p>
               <p>Suffer not thy Diſpleaſure to kindle and break out into a Flame againſt us.</p>
               <p>Turn from us that Wrath that as a juſt recompence of our Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations are due unto us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:33585:83"/>
Spare us according to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy Mercies.</p>
               <p>Lord Jeſus thou art the hope of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with the Lord there is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and with thee there is plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous redemption.</p>
               <p>Let thy Obedience recompence our Obſtinacy, thy Abſtinence our Superfluity, thy Meekneſs and Patience our Pride, Irefulneſs, and Enmity: Let thy Charity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence our Malice, thy Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion our Dulneſs, Love our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs; thy holy and precious Death our wretched &amp; ſinful Lives.</p>
               <p>But foraſmuch as thou reſiſteſt the Proud but give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Grace to the Humble, thou filleſt the Hungry with good things, but the Rich thou ſendeſt empty away.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:33585:83"/>
Therefore empty us of our <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odicean</hi> Riches, diſcover our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Poverty, and ſet home to our Conſciences the weight and danger of our Sins.</p>
               <p>Suffer not our Conſciences to let us be quiet until they have drawn us before thee in all Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Brokenneſs of Spirit in Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, as one is in Bitterneſs for the loſs of their Firſt-born, and confeſſing our ſelves loathing the Perſons as well as the Actions: With Deteſtation and Self-abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, and with indeclinable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves of Amendment of Life.</p>
               <p>In regard there muſt be a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of our Actions as well as of our Perſons, if our Sins riſe not again in this World to bring us to ſhame and confuſion of face and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:33585:84"/>
unfeigned and ſincere Repentance, they will riſe again in the World to come, and be as ſo many Ghoſts and Devils, and torment us for ever and ever. We had better judge our ſelves than put God to judge us.</p>
               <p>Therefore, O God, by thy powerful voice raiſe our Sins that are graved in oblivion, and ſet them in order before us, that we may break them down by repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
               <p>Thou canſt teach us to gather Grapes of Thorns and Figgs of Thiſtles, becauſe all things are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible unto thee. There is no Evil ſo great, but thou canſt bring good out of it.</p>
               <p>We turn Gold into Droſs, but
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:33585:84"/>
thou canſt turn Droſs into Gold again.</p>
               <p>Therefore be intreated, thou Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty One, that in regard we are ſuch miſerable Sinners, that our Sins may make us humble, for humility is in the ſight of God of great price.</p>
               <p>And in regard we are ſo evil, that we may be more charitable in judging of others, let our own unworthineſs hang ſo in our light, that we may not be too buſie in medling with others.</p>
               <p>And in regard we are ſuch great Debtors to Divine Juſtice, that we may be more charitable in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving others: That we may take heed of taking our Brother by the Throat, leſt thou call us to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33585:85"/>
and caſt us into priſon, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til we have paid the utmoſt far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>And in regard we are ſuch no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Criminals, that we may adore the light of the glory of God that ſhineth in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, to the praiſe and glory of his grace.</p>
               <p>And in regard we have ſpent ſo much time in rebellion, and yet thou art ready to ſhew mercy, that therefore we may look upon our ſelves in future as perſons ingaged to walk before thee in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and holineſs all our days.</p>
               <p>Spiritualize our Affections eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day more and more.</p>
               <p>Irradiate our Souls with high ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:33585:85"/>
and ſo elevate us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſelf, where true Riches are to be had.</p>
               <p>We ſtand as poor Beggars with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, but in conſideration how thou feedeſt thy people with deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacies, in the perfection of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, peace, and joy.</p>
               <p>O God we have heard with our ears, and our Fathers have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto us the noble works that thou doſt in Heaven and Earth. O Lord ariſe, help and deliver us for thine honour.</p>
               <p>Bring us out of the Land of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> and out of the houſe of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, that thou maiſt feed us with Manna from Heaven, and that we may offer unto God acceptable Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:33585:86"/>
Make out unto us that thou art our God and we thy peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>That we may live in abſolute reſignation, ſubjection, and love unto thee.</p>
               <p>Diſcover unto us the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the World, that our Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions may be taken off from the World.</p>
               <p>The wiſe man truſteth in his wiſdom, the ſtrong man in his ſtrength, and the rich man in his riches.</p>
               <p>The ſhip-wrack'd man catcheth hold on what is next him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> ſhip-wrack'd us all, and we are floating in a Deluge of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity:
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:33585:86"/>
Man is born unto trouble, as the Sparks flie up ward; and in this wretchedueſs we naturally catch hold on ſomething; Self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation being a clear Dictate of Nature: But our ignorance and miſapprehenſion make us to catch at deceitful things, that fill every one that truſt in them with diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment: ſome on Honour, ſome on Pleaſure, ſome on Riches: And here they abide until God ſhew them a more excellent way. What ever the Objects of our Souls are, we ſhall not deſert them until bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Objects be diſcovered unto us.</p>
               <p>Altho it be an unſatisfied ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that we enjoy by any ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary thing, yet when we know of no better, we hold faſt by what we have.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:33585:87"/>
Therefore we pray for ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of that glory that ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward be revealed; of thoſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-dying comforts for our never-dying ſouls.</p>
               <p>'Tis but an unquiet quiet and a reſtleſs reſt, that we enjoy from the Creature: We pray for the Contentment above the World, which is better than the World without that Contentment.</p>
               <p>Ever ſince thou draveſt out the Man, we have been ſeeking reſt, but have found none.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Noah</hi>'s Dove could find no reſt for the ſole of her foot until ſhe return'd into the Ark again, neither is there any reſt for us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til we return and center in our God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:33585:87"/>
Now when we turn our faces towards thee, for we know not what to do, but our Eyes are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee; take us into the Ark of the Covenant.</p>
               <p>We are very much foil'd with walking after the ſight of our own eyes and deſires of our own hearts; take us into thy protection, that we may lay us down in peace, for thou makeſt thy people to dwell in ſafety.</p>
               <p>Embrace us in the arms of thy mercy.</p>
               <p>Hide us under the Covert of thy Wings, cover us with the Canopy of thy Love, that we may feel thy Power ſupporting us, and thy Goodneſs ſupplying us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:33585:88"/>
That we may rejoyce in thee as our Treaſure, and reſt in thee as our Center.</p>
               <p>In this far Countrey we thought to have met with great matters, when we ran away from thee; but we find nothing but Husks which Swine feed upon; and gladly we would fill our Bellies with them, but cannot: Here is no ſoul-ſuitable nor ſoul-ſatisfying good, therefore we find it abſolutely neceſſary to return to our Fathers Houſe, where there is Bread enough and to ſpare; there being infinite Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Manſions at thy right hand. With thee is that River of Pleaſure, in which our Souls may bathe with infinite delight, even for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>Take us into Favour, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:33585:88"/>
us with a Fatherly Affection.</p>
               <p>When we cry unto the Lord with our voice, let him hear us out of his holy Hill.</p>
               <p>Doubtleſs thou art our Father, thou art the Potter, we are the Clay; it is thou that haſt made us, and not we our ſelves. We are thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ſheep of thy paſture.</p>
               <p>Where is thy Zeal and the ſounding of thy Bowels and of thy Mercies, are they reſtrained? <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> is ignorant of us, and <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> acknowledgeth us not. We cannot have confidence in Saint or Angel, but thou art our God, in thy Word is our hope, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we lift up our eyes to the Hills, from whence cometh our hope. Our help cometh from the Lord,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:33585:89"/>
who made Heaven and Earth.</p>
               <p>Cauſe thy Providences and thy Promiſes to meet together, and kiſs each other, in opening to us that knock, in being found of them that ſeek thee.</p>
               <p>Lord ſeparate us from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon condition of incapacity and indiſpoſition.</p>
               <p>Disband and looſen our Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from all Terrene Beauties.</p>
               <p>Convince us how good it is to draw nigh unto thee.</p>
               <p>We erre in our hearts, becauſe we do not know thy ways.</p>
               <p>We eſteem not our God as we ought, becauſe of the ignorance that is in us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:33585:89"/>
Lighten our eyes, leſt that we ſleep the ſleep of death.</p>
               <p>Purge our minds enough from the earthy dregs of Senſe and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>Bring thy Ark into our Hearts, that <hi>Dagon</hi> may fall down.</p>
               <p>Cauſe <hi>Aaron</hi>'s rod to ſwallow up the Egyptians Rods.</p>
               <p>That the Stone cut out with hands may pound <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi>'s Image to duſt.</p>
               <p>Cloath us with the Sun, and we ſhall tread the Moon under our Feet.</p>
               <p>That the Priviledges we may enjoy by our Lord Chriſt, our moſt
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:33585:90"/>
bleſſed Redeemer and Saviour, may melt all our other Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments into Nullities, and implanr in us a diſeſtimation of all the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearments that we uſe to feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here below.</p>
               <p>We have loſt thee by Pride, we hope to find thee in Humility; we have loſt our God in Luxury, we hope to find thee in Abſtinence; we have loſt thee by Oppreſſion, we will ſeek thee in Reſtitution.</p>
               <p>Enlarge our Underſtandings, that the Diamond of Grace may hinder the Loadſtone of the World from drawing our hearts after it.</p>
               <p>That we may be gain'd upon ſo much by Heavenly Things, that Earthy Things may have no power on us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:33585:90"/>
That the Luſtre of the Pearl of Price may make the Worlds glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to diſappear.</p>
               <p>Open our Eyes, that we may ſee the Banner of the Goſpel, that we may become Voluntiers, and run to Chriſt's Standard.</p>
               <p>That we may account all things but loſs and droſs and dung, in compariſon of the Excellency of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>Wean us from the World, that we may look towards our Maker, and have reſpect to the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cloath us with a holy Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency and Neutrality in having or wanting Earthy Things.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:33585:91"/>
That we may have a ſteady com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure and an uninterrupted ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of mind, thro an unſhaken ſubmiſſion to, acquieſcence in, and conformity to the will of God in all Occurrences, even in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Storms to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to God's <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Inſtruct us and teach us what we ſhould do, and guide us with thine Eye.</p>
               <p>Be thou as the Dew unto us, that we may grow as the Lilly, and caſt forth our Roots as <hi>Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> that our Branches may ſpread, and our Beauty as the Olive Tree, and our ſmell as <hi>Lebanon,</hi> that we may ſay with <hi>Ephraim, What have we to do any more with Idols?</hi> And that our Fruit may be found from thee. Make us all Obedience, by
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:33585:91"/>
an infallible Reſignation without Exception, Reſervation, or Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p>That thy Will may be our Rule, thy Spirit our Guide, thy Precepts the Rule of our Practices, and thy Decrees our Delight.</p>
               <p>Our own Strength is never ſo untruſty as when it is moſt truſted, therefore ſtay our ſteps in thy paths, that our feet ſlide not.</p>
               <p>Fill our Reſolutions with the hope of Glory, that we may preſs forward towards the high price of our Calling with facility and ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity.</p>
               <p>Set open the Gates of thy Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Favours to us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:33585:92"/>
Draw us with the Favours of thy good Oyntments, for it is therefore the Virgins love thee.</p>
               <p>That we may be always in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with God.</p>
               <p>That we may every day learn a Vertue and damn a Vice.</p>
               <p>Hide not thy Face from us, leſt we be found amongſt them that go down into the Pit.</p>
               <p>In regard that Chriſt our Lord is gone to prepare a place for us, that we may prepare our ſelves for that place.</p>
               <p>In regard that Jeſus was crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for our Sins ſake; help us to mortifie our Sins for Jeſus's ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:33585:92"/>
Beſtow ſome taſtes of thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love upon us, the Earneſt of the Spirit: Then ſhall we be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that all the miſeries of this life are not worthy to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with that glory that ſhall after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be revealed.</p>
               <p>Inrich our Souls with all the Moveables of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Beſtow upon us the Spirit of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and Fidelity, too bey all the adored Commands of our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable Redeemer, that we may anſwer all the inſpiring Calls of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety.</p>
               <p>Give unto us all thoſe degrees of Grace and Sanctity; thoſe Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Movements towards the Kingdom of Glory, that we may arrive at the unſpeakable Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:33585:93"/>
of thy Eternal Viſion, which is Eſſential Happineſs, of ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and Super-eminent Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, containing all Wiſdom, all Learning, all Knowledge, all Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, all Fulneſs and Satisfaction, and all other Cauſes of Love, Joy, and Contentation, wherein our Souls may reſt for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>Let our Vertues and Graces be acquainted with no other Seaſon but a Spring, and let nothing skreen us from thoſe Beams that ſhould ripen all our good Deſires into Enjoyments.</p>
               <p>Father of Mercies do good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Mankind.</p>
               <p>Oh the Bondage, the Burden, the Guilt, that the World hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted!</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:33585:93"/>
The World lieth in Wickedneſs, Vice hath invaded the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Man.</p>
               <p>The Giants of Sin are grown to full ſtature.</p>
               <p>Oh how Iniquity hath advanced her ſelf in the hearts of Men.</p>
               <p>The height of Iniquity is come to the top, the Fruit thereof is ripe and ready to drop upon us.</p>
               <p>Sin is rampant.</p>
               <p>The World goeth awry to dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>The paths of <hi>Sion</hi> do weep and wail for want of paſſengers.</p>
               <p>What is become of Charity,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:33585:94"/>
Truth, Sincerity, Humility, and Piety: Oh they are flown to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, from whence they came, and have left the dangerous Succeſſors Falſhood, Cruelty, Pride, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and Prophaneneſs.</p>
               <p>Religion is in its laſt Period, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying by little and little, entring the Cold Chillneſs of Dying Age.</p>
               <p>Not one in Forty thouſand in whoſe hand a Spear or Shield is found.</p>
               <p>Even all are imbarked in the Bold Adventure for Hell.</p>
               <p>Pride, Oppreſſion, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs ride in Proſperous Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs without Controul, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the face of the Earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:33585:94"/>
Vice braves it with a bolden'd Face.</p>
               <p>Sin is in its Power, Corruption is upon its Throne.</p>
               <p>Take away the Covering that covereth the face of all People.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:33585:95"/>
               <head>For the CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH.</head>
               <p>WE have had a long Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, but ſmall Harveſt.</p>
               <p>Increaſe the precious Sons of <hi>Sion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Call thy Sons from far, and thy Daughters from the ends of the Earth; that they may be called by thy Name.</p>
               <p>Let all the Nations of the Heathen become the Kingdom of the Lord Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:33585:95"/>
Take in the Heathen for thine Inheritance, and the Utmoſt Parts of the Earth forthy Poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>Let all the People praiſe thee, O God, yea let all the People praiſe thee.</p>
               <p>Cauſe all the Kindred of the Nations to worſhip before thee, and lead them in the Paths of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs for thy Names ſake.</p>
               <p>Caſt thy Net into the Seas, and gather of all Kinds.</p>
               <p>That the Sun of the Goſpel may riſe to ſuch an Altitude, that it may inlighten every Dark Corner of the Earth.</p>
               <p>That the World that is gene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ruled by the Malicious Prince
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:33585:96"/>
of Darkneſs, may now receive and obey thy Holy Laws in the Beauty and Harmony of Holineſs.</p>
               <p>Search thy Sheep, and ſeek them out as a Shepard ſeeketh out his Flock in the Day that he is among his Sheep, and deliver them out of all places where they have been ſcattered in the cloudy and dark Day.</p>
               <p>Feed them upon <hi>Lebanon,</hi> by the Rivers, that they may lie them down in peace.</p>
               <p>Seek that which is Loſt, Bring again that which is Driven away, Bind up that which is Broken, and ſtrengthen that which is Sick.</p>
               <p>Cauſe thy ſaving health to be known among all Nations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:33585:96"/>
Pull down the Strong Holds of Satan, build up the Walls of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and gather together the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſts of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lamentable are the breaches and ruins of thy Church, ſcarce one ſtone left upon another.</p>
               <p>Thou art the Owner thereof, and able enough, therefore repair it.</p>
               <p>Thy Vineyard looks very wild, and inſtead of Grapes it bringeth forth Wild Grapes; Oh prune it and fence it, cleanſe away the Impurity, Sinfulneſs, and Defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it.</p>
               <p>Suffer no Root of Schiſm, Slip of Error, or Fruit of Diſobedience, to grow in thy Garden.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:33585:97"/>
Cauſe the North Wind to ariſe, and the South Wind to blow, that the Spices may flow out.</p>
               <p>Adorn the Profeſſion of Religion with an Acceſſion of a Bleſſing.</p>
               <p>That the Sun of Righteouſneſs may inliven the Church to a higher pregnancy.</p>
               <p>That the Innate Power of the Goſpel may prove ſo Victorious, that Paganiſm, Mahumatiſm, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſm, Atheiſm, and Papiſm, may melt under the powerful Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it.</p>
               <p>Oh feed thy Flock and fold them.</p>
               <p>Thou who commandeſt the Clouds from above, and openeſt the Windows of Heaven, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:33585:97"/>
and refreſh thine Inheritance with Showers of Divine Favour, leaſt it prove like a Heath in the Deſart.</p>
               <p>Open the Coeleſtial Caſements<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſhowre down Goſpel Bleſſings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>If our Root be not Rottenneſs, Heavenly Waterings and Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will make it ſprout forth into Fruits of Obedience.</p>
               <p>Send down the ſpirit of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and Fidelity, that the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored Commands of our aimia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Redeemer may be obeyed.</p>
               <p>Reform thoſe parts of thy Church that are dark'ned and defiled: Caſt down that Tyranny, Hereſie, and Schiſm, which keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out Truth, Holineſs, and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:33585:98"/>
Peace; that Truth may triumph over Errour.</p>
               <p>That the Streams of Truth, in the Banks of Unity, may make glad the City of God.</p>
               <p>That Right may be reſtored, Worth prized, Vertue honoured, Vice degraded, and Honeſty and Godlineſs encouraged.</p>
               <p>Set Bounds to our Paſſions by Reaſon, to our Errors by Truth, to our Seditions by Laws, to our Schiſms by Charity, that the Church may be as a City at Unity in it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Fire of Divine Love to burn up and conſume all Roughneſs, Hatred, and Cruelty, that a Willing and Peaceful Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:33585:98"/>
may be-calm the World.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Ephraim</hi> may not envy <hi>Judah,</hi> nor <hi>Judah</hi> vex <hi>Ephraim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shew thy Compaſſions unto them who are upon the Mountains of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> where there are no Dews, and in <hi>Egypt,</hi> where there are no Showres: thou art ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for them.</p>
               <p>Shew Pity and Favour unto them who are toſſed to and fro upon the Main of Ignorance, with every Wind of Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Bring them under a powerful Spiritual Teaching, from the Heart to the Heart, from the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Conſcience, from Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience to Experience.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:33585:99"/>
Eſpecially favour this Part of thy Church in this Kingdom, that it may be a Paradiſe of Pleaſure, the Garden of God; that the Valleys may be like <hi>Eden,</hi> the Hills like <hi>Lebanon,</hi> the Springs like <hi>Piſgah,</hi> and the Rivers like <hi>Jordan,</hi> and the Defence thereof the Lord <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cauſe thy Spirit as a mighty Eaſt Wind to diſperſe the Locuſts.</p>
               <p>That our Nation may be as a Field which the Lord hath bleſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:33585:99"/>
               <head>For the KING.</head>
               <p>IN a moſt Eminent Manner give Demonſtrations of thy Favour unto our Moſt Dread Soveraign Lord <hi>CHARLES,</hi> by thy Grace of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> King; Defender of the Faith: and in all Cauſes and over all Perſons, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Civil, in theſe His Majeſties Realms and Dominions, Supream Head and Governour.</p>
               <p>Let him be precious in thy Sight.</p>
               <p>Watch over him for Good.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:33585:100"/>
Cauſe all Deſigns that are againſt him to prove abortive.</p>
               <p>Make his Enemies to be as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> was before the Ark, fallen down and broken in pieces; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving neither Heads to plot, nor Hands to fight againſt Him.</p>
               <p>As thou haſt placed him on high above us, make thy Bleſſings ſuitable to his Exaltation and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>Let not the Sun of his Proſperity decline, but when his Courſe is finiſhed here below, he may aſcend into the Unchangeable Glory, and be cloathed upon, and be a Star of the Firſt Magnitude; ever ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Heaven of Heavens.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:33585:100"/>
               <head>For the Miniſters of the GOSPEL.</head>
               <p>PLace in every one of us an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-flowing Fountain, that we may not onely be conſtant, but abundant, in the Work of the Lord.</p>
               <p>That we may be a Means to mollifie their hard Hearts, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak their Love to God: Let us be more and more under the Influences and rich Pourings of thy Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:33585:101"/>
Make ut Maſters of great Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Experience in Soul Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</p>
               <p>That we may weild the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of our Warfare, which are not Carnal, to the beating down of every high and towring Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that ſhall exalt themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kingdom of our Lord Chriſt.</p>
               <p>That with ſweet Inſinuations and a holy Importunity, we may compel them to come in, that thy Houſe may be filled, and thy Feaſt furniſhed with Gueſts.</p>
               <p>Inſpire us with Zeal and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry.</p>
               <p>That we may partake of the Fountain of Wiſdom, and drink
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:33585:101"/>
of the River of Knowledg, that in us may be the Vein of Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>Impregnate us with Divine No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in ſuch abundance, that we may have teeming Wombs to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich the World.</p>
               <p>Adorn and Beautifie us with ſuch a Brightneſs of Wiſdom and Underſtanding, that we may ſparkle with raviſhing heat of Love and Piety.</p>
               <p>That the Divine Image may fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be reflected on us, that it may ſhine brightly in the Faces of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Fill us with Prudence and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: Mould many and Wiſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, Mature Determinations,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:33585:102"/>
deep Notions holy and pious Counſels, for the Teaching and Carrying on of thy Flock.</p>
               <p>That we may be as precious Jewels to inrich the World.</p>
               <p>Communicate unto us the Sublime Myſteries of Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
               <p>That our Lips may drop the Words of Life.</p>
               <p>And that our Tongues may be as a Tree of Life, whoſe leaves are Medicinable.</p>
               <p>Give unto us the Light of Divine Knowledge in the Purity of Divine Truth.</p>
               <p>Inrich us in all Knowledg, in all
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:33585:102"/>
Utterance, and in all Workman ſhip.</p>
               <p>Inlighten our Eyes, that we may ſee quite through the Depths of Divinity.</p>
               <p>Reveal unto us by thy Spirit, for the Spirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God.</p>
               <p>Give us leave to plow with thy Heifer; and we ſhall find out the Riddls.</p>
               <p>Great is the Myſtrey of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Who is ſufficient for theſe things? Attract our Minds by thy Spirit, that our Flight may be high, and we ſhall ſing more ſweetly.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:33585:103"/>
Suffer not the Sun to go down over the Prophets, let it not be dark over their Heads.</p>
               <p>Fill us with the Spirit of God in Wiſdom, in Underſtanding, in Knowledg, and in Workmanſhip, that we may undeceive many.</p>
               <p>Make us Paſtors according to thy own Heart, that we may feed thy People with Wiſdom and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</p>
               <p>Furniſh us with all the Requiſites that ſhould belong to Goſpel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
               <p>So qualifie us with Ability and Integrity, that Envy her ſelf may be forced to confeſs that we are Workmen that need not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:33585:103"/>
Suffer us not to be as Clouds without Rain, like empty Clouds that deceive thirſty Souls.</p>
               <p>Bleſs our Labours to great Meaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
               <p>To whom hath the Arm of the Lord been revealed?</p>
               <p>Who hath believed our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port?</p>
               <p>Shall the Trumpet beblown, and the People not affraid? Shall the Lyons roar, and the Beaſts of the Forreſt not tremble.</p>
               <p>Cloath us with a great deal of Mind, that we may diſtil many wholſom Notions and rectified Apprehenſions into the Minds of Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:33585:104"/>
That we may bring Truth which is ſo far abſent, home into Mens Boſomes.</p>
               <p>That we may uſe both the Harp and the Arrows, that our Speech be ſweet and piercing.</p>
               <p>That we may feaſt the hungry Ears with Delicious Dainties.</p>
               <p>Give unto us the Tongue of the Learned, that we may ſpeak a Word in due ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>The Grace of God and the mighty Spirit of Jeſus, work in us, that we may be inabled to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Weak, to confute the Obſtinate, to reclaim the Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to confirm the Faithful, and to comfort the Dejected and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:33585:104"/>
Make us happy Inſtruments of much Glory unto thy Name, and of much good unto thy People.</p>
               <p>Suffer not the Fruits of our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to fail: Give a Bleſſing to our Endeavours; <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, and <hi>Apollo</hi> may water, but thou onely giveſt the Increaſe.</p>
               <p>Except the Lord build the Houſe, they labour but in vain that build it; except the Lord keep the City, the Watchman watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but in vain.</p>
               <p>Cauſe our Words which we ſpeak from thee, to be as Goads and Nails faſten'd by the Maſters of the Aſſembly.</p>
               <p>Suffer not our Knowledg to be without Zeal, nor our Zeal with out Knowledg.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:33585:105"/>
Make us not onely Voices cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but Lights ſhining.</p>
               <p>That we may not onely be Trees of Knowledg, but Trees of Life, in the Paradiſe of our God.</p>
               <p>Give unto us to know the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of of the Kingdom of God.</p>
               <p>Teach us to find much of the Treaſure hid in the Field.</p>
               <p>Make us uſeful and ſucceſsful.</p>
               <p>That we may gather many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Triumphing Wings of Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Inable us to unmaſk and unvail Heavenly Truths, that each eye may ſee their Beauty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:33585:105"/>
That we may ſet ſuch a luſtrre upon the Pearl of Price, and ſo preſent Divinity in her graceful Jewels, that every one may be inamour'd with her.</p>
               <p>That we may lead Affection by the hand, and with a ſweet facility ſlide ſome Divine Truths into the Hearts of our Hearers.</p>
               <p>Grant that in all things we may approve our ſelves as Miniſters of God.</p>
               <p>That our Lights may ſo ſhine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Men, that they may ſee our Good Works and glorifie thee our Father which art in Heaven.</p>
               <p>Suffer us not to be Strangers to that Holineſs We preſs upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:33585:106"/>
Make us feed by Doctrine and feed by Example.</p>
               <p>Suffer not the Salt to loſe its Savour.</p>
               <p>Suffer not the Curſe to come upon us, like Prieſt like People.</p>
               <p>Suffer us not to pull down with one hand what we build with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, leſt the Sons of <hi>Levi</hi> cauſe the Offering of the Lord to be had in abomination.</p>
               <p>Dead Files cauſeth the Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Apothecary to ſend forth a ſtinking Savour, ſo doth a little Folly he that is in reputation for Wiſdom and Honour! there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtay our ſteps in thy Paths, that our feet ſlide not.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:33585:106"/>
That the Purity of Divine Truths may be unfolded in our hearts and lives.</p>
               <p>We have our Treaſure in Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Veſſels, purifie and cleanſe them, leſt thy Word have a tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of our Uncleanneſs.</p>
               <p>That we may not ſound the Lords Trumpet with a Stinking Breath.</p>
               <p>Cloath us with Righteouſneſs the Garments of Praiſe, and the Saints ſhall ſhout for joy.</p>
               <p>Grant that we may Credit the Goſpel, with Examplary Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</p>
               <p>That our Lives as well as Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, may continually teach Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:33585:107"/>
of Faith, Knowledg, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Patience, Brotherly Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Charity.</p>
               <p>That there may be ſeen what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are true, lovely, pure, vertuous, or praiſe worthy.</p>
               <p>That every one of us may be as a Torch on a Hill to inlighten all about us.</p>
               <p>Make us as Wiſe as Serpents, but as Innocent as Doves.</p>
               <p>They who are call'd to the Work, give them Grace to work in their Callings, that we may be true Servants and Friends of God.</p>
               <p>That we may lay up and lay out.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:33585:107"/>
O Lord help us that we may live above the Dependance and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuities of this vain World.</p>
               <p>That our Aim may be higher than the Eating of a Piece of Bread.</p>
               <p>That we may be free from the Blood of all Men, give us Grace to warn all Men, and to teach every Man in all Wiſdom; that we may preſent our Flocks acceptable before Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Whilſt our Tongues run at the ſervice of the Altar, God forbid that our Eyes ſhould ſquint at the Fat of the Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>Grant that we may not ſeek our ſelves but thee.</p>
               <p>Let our Endeavours be rather
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:33585:108"/>
for the profit than the pleaſure of the People.</p>
               <p>Strengthen us to live above Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, yea above Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements.</p>
               <p>That we may chiefly mind our Duty, and depend upon thee, as our onely but our ſure Reward.</p>
               <p>Give us a ſtrong and clear ſenſe of what we ſpeak.</p>
               <p>Let nothing come out of our Mouths, but what is to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>Suffer not the Stars of the Church to ſhed black and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Influences.</p>
               <p>Suffer not our Trumpets to give
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:33585:108"/>
an uncertain Sound, then who ſhall prepare themſelves for the Battle.</p>
               <p>Make us all of one right mind, that we may ſpeak the ſame thing, that there may be no Diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, that we may be perfectly joyn'd together in the ſame Mind and Judgment.</p>
               <p>That we may all always be in Conjunction with Truth.</p>
               <p>That we may all prove ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant Lights, that the People cannot but chuſe us for Direction.</p>
               <p>That we may be as Tutular An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to our Flocks.</p>
               <p>And that we may make all good to Heavens Eye that we ſhew to the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:33585:109"/>
               <head>For a Bleſsing upon the WORD preached.</head>
               <p>O Lord cauſe thy Word to run, and be glorified.</p>
               <p>Ingrave thy Counſels in our Hearts.</p>
               <p>The fruitfulneſs of the Seed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth upon the Sun and the Rain.</p>
               <p>Let us not onely have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Ordinances, but thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in the Ordinances.</p>
               <p>Let us feel the inward Sweetneſs and Deliciouſneſs that truly are in Divine Truths.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:33585:109"/>
Confirm the Words of thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and perform the Counſel of thy Meſſengers.</p>
               <p>Shall our Lipps drop Honey, and they taſte no Sweetneſs.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Entrance of thy Word to give Light and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the Simple, that thy Statutes may be our Songs in the Houſe of our Pilgrimage.</p>
               <p>That the efflux of Life and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from God may beget in us a true and lively Faith.</p>
               <p>The Law of the Lord being perfect, cauſe it to convert the Soul, the Teſtimonies of the Lord being ſure, that they may make Wiſe the Simple: that the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Lord being right,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:33585:110"/>
may rejoyce the Heart; and the Commandments of the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pure, may inlighten the Eyes.</p>
               <p>Imprint thy Word in Living Characters upon the Vital Powers of our Souls.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the blind to ſee out of Obſcurity and out of Darkneſs.</p>
               <p>Our Sins are faſt rooted in us, the Branches are wide and large, lay the Axe cloſe to the Root of the Tree.</p>
               <p>Let thy Call not onely reach our Ears but our Hearts.</p>
               <p>That our Ears may not onely be tickl'd but our Hearts touch'd.</p>
               <p>That thy VVord may not onely dwell with us, but in us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:33585:110"/>
That we may not onely learn what to do, but do what we learn.</p>
               <p>That we may not onely talk like Chriſtians, but walk like Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
               <p>A good Profeſſion and a good Converſation, theſe two who God hath joyned together, let no Man put aſſunder.</p>
               <p>That we may be Companions of all them that fear thee and keep thy Commandments.</p>
               <p>That we may not onely be Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baliſts but Realiſts.</p>
               <p>That our Heads may not onely be full of Notions, but our Hearts full of Graces.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:33585:111"/>
That Chriſt Jeſus may not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be the Subject of our Tongues but the Object of our Hearts.</p>
               <p>That we may make it our Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yea our Meat and Drink, to do the Will of our Lord.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Word to prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, that we may meet with ſomething that may meet with us.</p>
               <p>That the Word of Chriſt may dwell in us in all Wiſdom, that his Teſtimonies may be our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and our Councellors, that it may be unto us the Power of God unto Salvation.</p>
               <p>Suffer not the Word to return void, but that it may accompliſh that which thou pleaſeſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:33585:111"/>
Quicken our Apprehenſions, ſtrengthen our Memories; let us not be like a Man, beholding his Natural Face in a Glaſs, and goeth away forgeting what manner of Man he was: but grant that the Secret of the Lord may be with us, that we may know his Covenant.</p>
               <p>When the Watchmen ſound the Lords Trumpet, that we may take alarm with ſtout reſolutions to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Lords Banner.</p>
               <p>That the Words of thy Lips may keep us from the Paths of the Deſtroyer.</p>
               <p>That the Goſpel may not onely come unto us in Word but in Power; in much Aſſurance, and in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:33585:112"/>
Suffer not the Word to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomb'd but inſhrin'd in us.</p>
               <p>That the Leaven may be hid within us, until the whole be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened; that all the powers of our Souls may reliſh of it.</p>
               <p>That we may be abundantly ſatisfied with the Fatneſs of thy Houſe, and that we may drink of the Rivers of thy Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Cauſe thy Word to be an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to effect our Repentance.</p>
               <p>Cauſe it to be as a Fire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume our Luſts, and as a Hammer to break our hard Hearts upon the Cuſhion of thy Mercy.</p>
               <p>Bore our Ears, that we may hear when thou ſpeakeſt in Mercy, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:33585:112"/>
thou wilt force us to hear when thou ſpeakeſt in Wrath.</p>
               <p>That we may bow to thy Septer of Mercy, leſt thou break us in pieces with the Rod of thy Wrath.</p>
               <p>Grant that our Eyes may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by taſting of the Honey of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Open our Eyes, that we may ſee the Worth and Excellency of the Pearls that are caſt before us, that we may gather them to inrich us, that we may be known by the Bridegroom at his coming, by the Gold that we have bought, and the White Rayment we have put on.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Word of Reconcila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to make ſuch a Conjunction
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:33585:113"/>
betwixt Chriſt and our Souls, that they may never be ſeparated.</p>
               <p>Grant that we may hear in thy Houſe of Inſtruction, leſt thou bring us to thy Houſe of Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>That we may hear thy Word leſt we bear the Rod.</p>
               <p>That we may turn at thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, that thou may'ſt pour thy Spirit upon us, and make known thy Words unto us, leſt thou hedg up our Way with Thorns, and make a Wall, that we cannot find our Paths.</p>
               <p>Thou art the Lord that muſt teach us to profit, that muſt lead us the way that we ſhould go; for thy Commandments are a Lamp,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:33585:113"/>
and thy Law a Light, and Reprooſs of Inſtruction are the Way of Life.</p>
               <p>Grant that the ſame Spirit that wrote the Word, may teach us to underſtand it.</p>
               <p>That through thy Precepts we may get Underſtanding, and by Underſtanding hate every falſe Way.</p>
               <p>Open our Eyes, that we may ſee the wondrous Things that are in thy Law.</p>
               <p>That we may follow the Star, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til we find Jeſus the Chriſt, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him.</p>
               <p>When the Scriptures are opened to our Underſtandings, then open our Underſtandings to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:33585:114"/>
That we may diſcern what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches.</p>
               <p>Quicken us with thy Precepts, that we may never forget them.</p>
               <p>That they may make us wiſe unto ſalvation, through faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>That the light in the Golden Candle-ſticks, may ſo illuminate us, that we may walk in thy paths without ſtumbling.</p>
               <p>Cauſe thy Word to take Root downward, that it may bear Fruit upward; that we may have reſpect unto all thy Commandments.</p>
               <p>Make the VVord to be as a Remora to ſtay our Carnal Deſires, which are Voyaging in the Ocean
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:33585:114"/>
of VVorldy and Sinful Pleaſures.</p>
               <p>Make us not onely conſtant, but conſcionable Hearers.</p>
               <p>That thy VVord may be in us, that Incorruptible Seed that liveth and abideth for ever.</p>
               <p>When we meet for the better make us better for the Meeting.</p>
               <p>They that ſerve the Lord, let them be accepted with favour, that their Prayers may reach unto the Clouds.</p>
               <p>Let the Eye of the Lord be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that fear him, and that hope in his mercy.</p>
               <p>Let the heart of them rejoyce that ſeek the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:33585:115"/>
That they may be ſatisfied with the goodneſs of thy Houſe, even with the goodneſs of thy Holy Temple.</p>
               <p>Dart in ſome Beams of Irreſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ible Light into our Minds.</p>
               <p>That the Word may be a ſavour of Life unto Life, and not of Death unto Death.</p>
               <p>Cauſe that Word that offereth Salvation to our Souls, be a means to bring our Souls to Salvation.</p>
               <p>Let the Word be transforming, that we may be aſſimulated into Chriſt's likeneſs</p>
               <p>Cauſe our Affections to receive a Touch from the Word, that they may be ſtirr'd up, kindled, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:33585:115"/>
That thy Meſſage unto us may engage us to become a willing Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the day of thy Power.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Word to be quick and powerful, quicker than a two-edged Sword; ſo quick as to quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us to every good duty: and ſo powerful to ſubdue the Old Man of Sin. Make it of ſuch force, as to make a Diviſion between us and our beſt beloved Sins.</p>
               <p>That the Sword of the Spirit may cut us off from the Wild O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live of Nature.</p>
               <p>That we may not onely be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Grace of Truth, but the Truth of Grace.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Dew to fall with the Manna.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:33585:116"/>
That the Dews of <hi>Hermon</hi> may fall upon the Hill of <hi>Sion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That we may bring forth Fruits as the Vines of <hi>Engedi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cauſe thy Doctrine to drop as the Rain, to diſtil as the Dew, as the ſmall Rain upon the tender Herb, and as the Dew upon the Graſs.</p>
               <p>Drive the Birds from the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
               <p>When we draw nigh unto thee in Duty, draw nigh unto us in Mercy. Let not them that wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee be aſhamed.</p>
               <p>Open the Doors of our Hearts, that the King of Glory may enter.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:33585:116"/>
Put a holy Fear into our Hearts that we may attend upon thee with Reverence.</p>
               <p>That we may not receive it as the word of a ſinful mortal Man, but as indeed and in truth it is, the Word of an Immortal God.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Word to be as a Bank, to hinder the Inundation of our Sins.</p>
               <p>Order our ſteps in thy Word, that Iniquity may not have Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over us.</p>
               <p>Make the Word to be as a Flaming Sword, to keep us from the forbiden Fruit: That it may be as a Curb to keep us from the ſtray of Offence.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:33585:117"/>
That we may obſerve to do what the Lord commandeth us, not turning to the right hand nor the left.</p>
               <p>That it may be as a Rudder to ſteer us in our right Courſe.</p>
               <p>Ingrave thy Counſels on the Frontiſpiece of our Hearts, and cauſe them to be evermore in an applicative practice.</p>
               <p>That we may grow by the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Milk of the Word.</p>
               <p>That as the Bee gathers the Flowers, and carrieth them home to the Hive, and worketh them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Honey, and liveth upon it in times of need; ſo help us, that we may gather the precious Truths out of thy holy Word, and carry
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:33585:117"/>
them home unto the Hive of our Hearts, and work them into Grace, and live upon it in a time of Trial.</p>
               <p>Lay hold on our Hearts by thy Omnipotent Grace.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Influences of thy Grace irreſiſtibly to ingage us to do thy will.</p>
               <p>That the manifeſtation of thy Grace, may be as Showers to parched Graſs, that our droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Souls that hang their Wings, may revive and leap for joy.</p>
               <p>That the Efflux of Life and power from God, may beget in us true and lively Faith.</p>
               <p>That Love may be enticed out of our ſelves to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:33585:118"/>
Cauſe Heavenly Ordinances to leave Fruitful Influences.</p>
               <p>That we may not onely enjoy the Goſpel of Peace, but the Peace of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>We deſire to ſun our ſelves in the Light of thy Countenance.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Word, like the Sun Beams, not onely to enlighten us, but heat and inliven us.</p>
               <p>Let it be Honey in the Mouth, Melody in the Ear, and a Jubile in the Heart.</p>
               <p>We ſee thy Foot-ſteps in the Creatures, but we wait to ſee thy Face in the Ordinances.</p>
               <p>Ordinances are the Pool of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſda,</hi>
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:33585:118"/>
that onely heal when the Spirit moveth the Waters.</p>
               <p>The Goſpel is the Pen, but the Holy Ghoſt is the Guider of it.</p>
               <p>Suffer not the Tree of Life to be too far from the Tree of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg.</p>
               <p>Cauſe Divine Truths to be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the Purity of our Hearts and Lives.</p>
               <p>That every Gale of Divinity may drive us nearer to the Haven of Felicity.</p>
               <p>That we may not be all for Speculation, but Senſation, to taſte how good the Lord is.</p>
               <p>Open the Paſſage between our Heads and our Hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:33585:119"/>
Convey ſome warm ſprinklings of thy Benediction into our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts.</p>
               <p>Suffer not any of us to be like <hi>Gideon</hi>'s dry Fleece.</p>
               <p>Let not the Thirſty Souls that wait for thee as the Rain, return like the Troops of <hi>Tema,</hi> with their Heads covered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:33585:119"/>
               <head>For <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate Men.</head>
               <p>IN mercy remember the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Children, that take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, but not of thee; and cover, but not with the covering of thy Spirit, that they may add Sin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sin.</p>
               <p>Whoſe Hearts are harden'd from thy Fear.</p>
               <p>Sin at the firſt was the cauſe of Ignorance, now Ignorance is the cauſe of Sin.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="190" facs="tcp:33585:120"/>
In the greatneſs of their Folly they go aſtray.</p>
               <p>Who never peep'd out of the Bondage of Senſual Luſt.</p>
               <p>They rebel againſt the Light, they know not the ways thereof, neither will they come into theſe Paths.</p>
               <p>Who walk after the vanity of their Minds, having their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding darken'd; being aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Life of God, thro the Ignorance that is in them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the blindneſs of their Hearts: who being paſt feeling, have given themſelves over to work all Uncleanneſs with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Their god is their Belly, their
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:33585:120"/>
glory is their ſhame; who mind Earthy things.</p>
               <p>There is a Bridle in their Jaws, which cauſeth them to err.</p>
               <p>Lord pity them, for they cannot pity themſelves.</p>
               <p>In provoking thee, they provoke their own damnation.</p>
               <p>Thou Being of Beings, have mercy upon them.</p>
               <p>Interrupt the Proceſs of their Extravagances.</p>
               <p>As they tread the paths of Death, let them ſee the drawn Sword of thy Diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>As they journey on in their Sins,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:33585:121"/>
cauſe a Light to ſhine from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>Amaze them with the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of their woful and wretched Eſtate.</p>
               <p>Suffer them not to breath quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, until they find the Fountain opened for Sin and for Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Set home unto their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the weight and danger of their Sins.</p>
               <p>That Conſcience may be as a Scorpion in the Boſom.</p>
               <p>Send the Fiery Serpents to ſting and wound them, that they may look after the Brazen Serpent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="193" facs="tcp:33585:121"/>
A wake them out of their Mortal Lethargy.</p>
               <p>Bring them out of the Womb of Natural Blindneſs, that they may be born again, altho they be Old.</p>
               <p>Thou who at firſt caus'd Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, ſay, <hi>Let there be Light,</hi> and there ſhall be Light.</p>
               <p>That the Day-ſpring from on high may viſit them that ſit in Darkneſs &amp; in the ſhadow of Death.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Day to dawn, and the Day Star to ariſe in their Hearts.</p>
               <p>Turn the Shadow of Death into the Morning.</p>
               <p>Let the Spirit of Conviction
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:33585:122"/>
come upon them, and a wake them as a Man that is a waked out of his Sleep.</p>
               <p>Our corrupt Nature is the moſt inexpugnable Fort in the World.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Dead to hear thy Voice and live.</p>
               <p>Of thoſe Stones raiſe up Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mollifie their hard Hearts, that are not penetrable, when the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of Conviction are ſhot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
               <p>Cauſe Hell to enter into them, that they may not enter into Hell.</p>
               <p>That thy terrors may affright them from thoſe evils which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="195" facs="tcp:33585:122"/>
Cauſe Sin to reign unto Death, that Grace may reign unto Eternal Life, thro Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>Snatch them as Brands out of the Fire, leſt they be ſwallowed up in their own ruins.</p>
               <p>Bring them out of their Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Bondage with a mighty Hand and a ſtretched-out Arm.</p>
               <p>The pleaſures of Sin, the power of Satan, and the ſource of Evil. Cuſtom, this three-fold Cord is not eaſily broken.</p>
               <p>Tranſlate them out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Satan into the glorious Liberty of the Children of God.</p>
               <p>Bring them from Darkneſs to Light, and from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan unto God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="196" facs="tcp:33585:123"/>
Glorifie thy ſelf by their ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not by their damnation.</p>
               <p>Turn their Vices into Vertues.</p>
               <p>Altho now they be afar off, make them nigh by the Blood of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Bring the Blind by a way they know not: Make Darkneſs Light unto them, and Crooked Paths ſtraight.</p>
               <p>O that Chriſt may be formed in them.</p>
               <p>That the Blind may ſee, the Deaf may hear, the Dumb may ſpeak, the Lame walk, and the Lepers may be cleanſed.</p>
               <p>We are all the Work of thy
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:33585:123"/>
Hands, make us all the Sheep of thy Paſture.</p>
               <p>We are all of one common Mold, make all of one common Salvation.</p>
               <p>Purge them with Hyſop, and they ſhall be clean.</p>
               <p>Say unto the dry bones live.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Leopards to change their Spots, and the Ethiopians their Hue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:33585:124"/>
               <head>For the Broken hearted.</head>
               <p>O God ſhew thy Grace to them whoſe ſouls deſire thee in the Night, that ſigh by reaſon of their bondage.</p>
               <p>Who thou haſt broke in the place of Dragons, and covered with the ſhadow of Death.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of a Man is able to bear his infirmity, but a Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Spirit who can bear.</p>
               <p>The troubles of the Spirit are the Spirit of troubles.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="199" facs="tcp:33585:124"/>
Even as the Wind, when it gets into the Caverns of the Earth, cauſeth it to quake, ſo Guilt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted and felt, maketh the poor ſoul to tremble.</p>
               <p>No Lyon roars like that in a Mans boſom.</p>
               <p>If a ſpark of thy Wrath be ſo terrible, when it flieth into our Conſciences; what will thy come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be, when thou comeſt with Flaming Fire, to render Vengance to thy Adverſaries?</p>
               <p>Their own Guilt hath brought two Hells in their Hearts, Horror and Shame.</p>
               <p>Oh ſin is of a Toady Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:33585:125"/>
After the ſtrong Wind, the Earthquake and the Fire cauſe the Still Voice to come.</p>
               <p>Hear the Cries out of the Deeps.</p>
               <p>Be thou their Pilot in the dark and dangerous Storm.</p>
               <p>Thou healeſt the Broken in Heart, and bindeſt up their Wounds.</p>
               <p>Let the ſighing of the Priſoners come before thee, and relieve them according to the greatneſs of thy Power.</p>
               <p>Bring the Priſoners from the Priſon, and them that ſit in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from the Priſon Houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="201" facs="tcp:33585:125"/>
Say to the Priſoners, Go forth, to them in Darkneſs, Shew your ſelves. Cauſe them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed in the ways, and their paſtures to be in high places.</p>
               <p>Pleaſures of Sin merried their Senſes for a while, but horror fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after, and vultures their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſuming Hearts, and thoſe that carried the moſt pleaſing taſtes, fit them with the largeſt reluctati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Oh ſympathize with the weary and heavy laden ones, how they long for the Scape-goat to carry their Sins into oblivion.</p>
               <p>They watch for him more than they that watch for the Morning.</p>
               <p>That look thro the Windows,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:33585:126"/>
and cry thro the Lateſſes, Why is his Chariot ſo long in coming? Why ſtay the wheels of his Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot?</p>
               <p>They who are ſick with the ſenſe of their miſery, comfort them with the ſweetneſs of thy mercy.</p>
               <p>They who ſee their miſeries out of Chriſt, cauſe them to ſee the light of the glory of God, that ſhineth in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt, to the praiſe and glory of his Grace.</p>
               <p>Looſe off their Sack-cloth, and gird them with gladneſs, that their glory may ſing praiſe.</p>
               <p>Break their Bonds, and they ſhall ſacrifice the ſacrifice of praiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="203" facs="tcp:33585:126"/>
Bind up the broken hearted, proclaim liberty to captives, open the priſon to them that are bound; comfort all that mourn, give them beauty for aſhes, the oyl of joy for mourning, and the garment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavinneſs, that they may be call'd Trees of Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>That they may be of the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed of the Lord, that return and come to <hi>Sion</hi> with Songs and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting joy upon their Heads.</p>
               <p>Cauſe true joy and gladneſs to poſſeſs their ſouls, that ſorrow and ſighing may fly away.</p>
               <p>Even as the eye of the Servant waiteth upon the hand of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or the Maiden upon the hand of her Miſtriſs, ſo they wait
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:33585:127"/>
upon thee, until thou haſt mercy on them.</p>
               <p>Cauſe them that lift up their ſouls unto thee, to know the way wherein they ſhould walk.</p>
               <p>Lead them to the door of hope opened in the valley of <hi>Achor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Be a Leader and Commander unto them, inſtruct them and teach them what they ſhould do, and guid them with thine eye: Guid theſe priſoners of hope unto the ſtrong holds.</p>
               <p>Remember them with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour thou beareſt unto thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and viſit them with thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p>They who are ſtung with the
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:33585:127"/>
Fiery Serpents, give them a ſight of the Brazen Serpent.</p>
               <p>The ſting of Death is Sin, the ſtrength of Sin is the Law; give them the Victory thro our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>That the great Phyſician of Souls may heal their Spiritual Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers.</p>
               <p>Where ſpiritual ſorrow ſinketh the heart, cauſe the pully of Faith to raiſe it.</p>
               <p>They who look towards thee with contrition, conſolate them with remiſſion.</p>
               <p>They who turn unto thee with humilation and repentance, turn unto them with commiſeration and forgiveneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="206" facs="tcp:33585:128"/>
According to thy promiſe, be with them that are of contrite and humble ſpirits, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones.</p>
               <p>Be nigh unto them that call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, that call upon thee in truth.</p>
               <p>Suffer not all their ſighs to wander in fleeting Air.</p>
               <p>Cauſe them that ſow in tears to reap in joy.</p>
               <p>Turn their mourning into dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, looſe off their ſack-cloth, and gird them with gladneſs.</p>
               <p>Cauſe thy Face to ſhine upon them, and they ſhall be ſaved.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="207" facs="tcp:33585:128"/>
They who are afflicted and toſſed with tempeſt, and are not comforted, lay their ſtones with fair Colours, and lay their Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations with Saphirs: Make their Windows of Agats, and their Gates of Carbuncles, and all their Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of pleaſant Stones.</p>
               <p>The Vapors of Sin are riſen and ingendred into a Cloud, which interpoſeth between them and the Sun of Mercy: Grant for the preſent that ſome glances from the edges of the interpoſed body may refreſh them.</p>
               <p>Where the ſtormy Clouds are riſen, when the diſtreſſed ones expect to be over-whelmed with the Deluge of thy Wrath, then ſet thy Bow in the Clouds.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="208" facs="tcp:33585:129"/>
A diſcovery of Free Grace will be precious.</p>
               <p>Make them to hear joy and gladneſs, that the bones that thou haſt broken may rejoyce.</p>
               <p>Bring them on Eagles Wings from <hi>Sinai</hi> to <hi>Sion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cauſe them that mourn to be exalted to ſafety.</p>
               <p>Open the Conduits of Soul-ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation and Soul-conſolation.</p>
               <p>Hope deferred maketh the heart ſick, but when the deſire cometh, it is a Tree of Life.</p>
               <p>Sin hath over-laid their hopes, O raiſe them from the dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="209" facs="tcp:33585:129"/>
Let down a beam of Comfort to temper their Deſpair.</p>
               <p>Contend not for ever, be not always wroth, then the ſpirits will fail, and the ſouls which thou haſt made.</p>
               <p>Teach them to feed on the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did of the Honey-comb. Out of the Eater came forth Meat, and out of the ſtrong came forth Sweetneſs.</p>
               <p>That they may be juſtified by Faith, and have peace with God thro our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Hang forth the White Flagg of Mercy, and lift up their Heads, that they may ſee their redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on drawing near.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="210" facs="tcp:33585:130"/>
Diſplay the Enſign of thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions, then ſhall they run to thy Standard.</p>
               <p>Help them that are under the pains and pangs of the New Birth, guid them in the way that leadeth to Everlaſting Life.</p>
               <p>Open unto them the Gates of Righteouſneſs, that they may go in and praiſe thy Name.</p>
               <p>Let the Lords Compaſſions reach to all that are wraſtling with and toſſed in the Sea of their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and are violently carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on with temptations, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power'd by their licentious Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in the Straits of Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that have much ado to keep off from the Rocks of Deſpair, and afraid to be ſwallow'd up in the Gulph of Perdition.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="211" facs="tcp:33585:130"/>
When they paſs thro the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, be thou with them. When they go thro the Rivers, ſuffer them not to over-flow them. When they walk thro the Fire, ſuffer them not to be burned, nor the flame to kindle upon them.</p>
               <p>Conſider their trouble, for thou knoweſt their ſouls are in adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
               <p>Turn the Bruiſed Reed into a Golden Pillar, and the Smoaking Flax into a Triumphing Flame.</p>
               <p>Be thou their Arm every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and their ſalvation in a time of trouble.</p>
               <p>Bring them from the depths of Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="212" facs="tcp:33585:131"/>
Glorifie thy ſelf in their Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances.</p>
               <p>Redeem <hi>Iſrael</hi> from all his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</p>
               <p>Swallow up Death in Victory, Wipe away tears from their Faces, and take away their Rebuke.</p>
               <p>Let the times of refreſhing come from the preſence of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Execute not the fierceneſs of thy Wrath, for thou art God and not Man.</p>
               <p>Caſt them not away from thy preſence, but uphold them with thy free ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Bind up the breach of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and heal the ſtroke of their wound.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="213" facs="tcp:33585:131"/>
For thy Names ſake defer thine anger and for thy Praiſe refrain.</p>
               <p>Guid them with thy Counſel, in order to their Reception into Glory.</p>
               <p>And comfort juſt <hi>Lot,</hi> that is vex'd with the unrighteous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of the Sodomites from day to day.</p>
               <p>How the ſecond Man the Lord from Heaven, the New Man, is plagued with the Hittites, the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, and the Jebuſites.</p>
               <p>The ſmall beginnings of Grace are preſerved by the powers from Heaven.</p>
               <p>The Sojourner is oppoſed and deſpiſed, becauſe of the contrariety between them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="214" facs="tcp:33585:132"/>
Damn'd <hi>Satan,</hi> the World, and the Fleſh, combine to extinguiſh that which thou haſt kindled.</p>
               <p>The Fleſh Iuſteth againſt the Spirit, and the Spirit againſt the Fleſh; theſe two are contrary the one to another.</p>
               <p>Relieve thy Servants who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the Holy War.</p>
               <p>When they walk thro the midſt of trouble, do thou revive them; ſtretch forth thy hand againſt the wrath of thine enemies, that thy right hand may ſave them.</p>
               <p>Support them with the Spirit of Power and the power of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p>Perfect that which concerneth
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:33585:132"/>
them, thy mercy O Lord endureth for ever; forſake not the Work of thine own hands.</p>
               <p>It is the Lord that bringeth forth his People from their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and lifteth them up on high above them.</p>
               <p>Corruption is always ſtrong enough to keep Grace low: Grant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Grace may prove ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to keep Corruption low.</p>
               <p>Suffer not their Corruptions to worry and devour the Fruits of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Take the Foxes that ſpoil the Vines, for the Vines have tender Grapes.</p>
               <p>Fill every one that hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="216" facs="tcp:33585:133"/>
Deny not thoſe ardent deſires of the bliſsful fruition of thy Self, which the lively ſenſe of thy own Goodneſs hath enkindled; thoſe breathings and gaſpings for an eternal participation of thee.</p>
               <p>The Soul is depreſſed with an unpaſſable thicket of hinderances, the frailties of the Body, the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of the World, and the ſpiritual Enemies that continually war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Goodneſs; they are ever checking the production of thoſe good motions ſhe is pregnant with.</p>
               <p>Oh ſend a ſpring of auxilliary Grace to actuate the dull habits of inherent Grace.</p>
               <p>Thou knoweſt their wo becauſe they dwell in <hi>Meſech,</hi> and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:33585:133"/>
to dwell in the Tents of <hi>Kedar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lead forth thy people whom thou haſt redeemed, and guid them with thy ſtrength to thy holy Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation.</p>
               <p>Open the Rivers in high places, and Fountains in the midſt of the Valleys: Make the Wilderneſs a Pool of Water, and the dry Land Springs of Water.</p>
               <p>The whole World cannot ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their Spiritual Longings, give them Soul-ſuitable Returns.</p>
               <p>The Good that they would do, that do they not, the Evil that they would not do, that do they; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Law of the Members that war againſt the Law of the Mind.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="218" facs="tcp:33585:134"/>
They would gladly be with thee, but they cannot get near becauſe of the Croud.</p>
               <p>Their Souls thirſt upon the Croſs, but Gall and Vinegar is their Drink.</p>
               <p>Shall not the good Angel mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter unto them.</p>
               <p>Help them who are troubled with vexing Scruples, and reduced to dark Perplexities.</p>
               <p>When they go forward thou art not there, and when they go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they cannot perceive thee: Oh manifeſt thy ſelf unto them.</p>
               <p>Cauſe thy Grace to guid their ſlippery ſteps.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="219" facs="tcp:33585:134"/>
And unto them who thou haſt in ſome meaſure given Victory to, make the Habitation of their Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs proſperous.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Righteous to hold on his Way, and he that hath clean Hands to be ſtronger and ſtronger.</p>
               <p>That they may grow in Grace, and from one degree of Grace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Light of the Righteous to ſhine more and more unto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Day.</p>
               <p>Suffer not <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt to over-take them.</p>
               <p>Suffer them not to look back to <hi>Egypt,</hi> nor to long after the Garlick and the Onions.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="220" facs="tcp:33585:135"/>
That they may rather think of the burden and bondage, and the woful circumſtances and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of Sin, than the vain plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of it.</p>
               <p>Suffer them not to be plagued with Satans return or any freſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions or revolutions of their old Sins.</p>
               <p>Thou who ſetteſt them up, and makeſt them holy, keep them up, and make them ſteady.</p>
               <p>Keep them from lapſes and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varications.</p>
               <p>Let them not want the Pillar of a Cloud by Day, nor the Pillar of Fire by Night.</p>
               <p>Let the Bleſſed Spirit, which was
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:33585:135"/>
the Pre-operator, be the Co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator; leſt they return to the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fight their battles and ſupply their wants.</p>
               <p>Give them a clear ſight of the Crown of Immortality that the joys of that which is ſet before the eyes of their Faith, may ſtill refreſh them, that they may endure unto the End.</p>
               <p>Give them a Sample of what they are preſſing toward, and ſometimes a Taſte of the Fruits of <hi>Canaan,</hi> that they may reſolve to fight with the Sons of <hi>Anack.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fraught them ſo with hope that they may venture into any ſtorm.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="222" facs="tcp:33585:136"/>
That they may be ſatisfied that all the miſeries of this life is not worthy to be compared with that glory that ſhall afterward be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</p>
               <p>That all the thoughts of miſery may be drowned in the precious deeps of Eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="223" facs="tcp:33585:136"/>
               <head>For the Afflicted.</head>
               <p>O Lord be Gracious to all them that are under the Wring of Sorrow and in the Preſs of Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
               <p>That are Wounded with the Weapons of thy Indignation, and caſt down with the Evidences of thy Diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>That are ſunk into Inconſolable Afflictions, captivated and fetter'd in the Darkſom Priſon of Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedneſs, and hurried upon the Shelves and Rocks of Infelicity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="224" facs="tcp:33585:137"/>
We humbly own thou mighteſt juſtly have made us Examples un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, our ſins was in the Cry that brought down Vengeance.</p>
               <p>We are not ſpared becauſe we are more righteous, but becauſe to us thou art more gracious.</p>
               <p>Thou dealeſt with us as with Princes Children, others are beaten for our faults, but 'tis intended for our amendment.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt diſtributed ſorrows in thine anger, and haſt broken them with breach upon breach.</p>
               <p>Thou reapeſt that glory in their calamity, that they robb'd thee of in their proſperity.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt builded againſt them
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:33585:137"/>
and incompaſſed them with Gall and Travel.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt fill'd them with Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, and made them drunken with Wormwood.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt ſpoken againſt them in thy Wrath, and vex'd them with thy ſore diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>Thy Wrath lieth hard upon them, thou haſt afflicted them with many waves.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt ſpread thy Net up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and haſt brought them down as the Fowls of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Terrors are turned upon them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they purſue their Souls like the Wind, the days of affliction have taken hold upon them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="226" facs="tcp:33585:138"/>
With thy ſtrong hand thou op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeſt thy ſelf againſt them.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt lifted them up to the Wind.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt wrote bitter things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and cauſed them poſſeſs the Sins of their Youth.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt ſeal'd up their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions in a Bagg.</p>
               <p>Their Foundation is over-flown with a Flood.</p>
               <p>Black Clouds have darken'd their day, Gall and Wormwood hath bitter'd their Cup.</p>
               <p>Afflictions are Stinging Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="227" facs="tcp:33585:138"/>
We humbly own Sin is both the Mother and the Nurſe of all Calamity.</p>
               <p>There's ſome of the Golden Calf in all our Suffering.</p>
               <p>They have betray'd themſelves into the Hands of Sorrow.</p>
               <p>Afflictions ſpring not out of the duſt nor trouble out of the ground.</p>
               <p>They have largely contributed to their own ruin.</p>
               <p>They have made Wings for thy Judgments, which made them come ſo ſwiftly upon them.</p>
               <p>Their Sins have been ſure Pullies to draw on unexpected Wrath.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="228" facs="tcp:33585:139"/>
Sin is the Venemous Root out of which ſpringeth all Calamities.</p>
               <p>Vengeance like a Blood-hound, hunteth and findeth out the Guilty.</p>
               <p>Their Life ſpendeth in Grief, and their days in ſighing; their Strength faileth becauſe of their Iniquity.</p>
               <p>They have trodden the Paths of Death, elſe they had not met with the Drawn Sword of thy Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p>They have neceſſitated thee to chaſtiſe them.</p>
               <p>Their Sin hath burned hot, and hath ſet on fire the Train of Gods Wrath.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="229" facs="tcp:33585:139"/>
They have ſtrung Gods Bow with the Cords of Iniquity.</p>
               <p>Their own Wickedneſs hath corrected them, and their own Backſlidings have caſt them down, as Trees and Garments are eaten up with Moths and Worms which they breed themſelves.</p>
               <p>The Vapors of Sin have aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that have made ſuch thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Clouds.</p>
               <p>Like Thunder-bolts and ſuch fearful Meteors, that fall upon the Earth from whence they had their original.</p>
               <p>Their Iniquities are gone over their Heads like a heavy Burthen.</p>
               <p>The Deluge of Impiety drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Old World.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="230" facs="tcp:33585:140"/>
The Fire of Luſt fetch'd fire from Heaven upon <hi>Sodom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Stinking Coruption of Manners breed the Plague.</p>
               <p>They have broken the Hedge, therefore the Serpent hath bit them.</p>
               <p>They have eaten the forbidden Fruit, therefore the Curſe is upon them.</p>
               <p>Their Quails are ſauced with thy Wrath.</p>
               <p>Sin hath been the Herauld that hath gone before, therefore Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are th' Attendants that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after.</p>
               <p>They have made paths in Sin,
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:33585:140"/>
therefore thou haſt made paths in Judgment.</p>
               <p>They are eating the Fruit of their own Ways, and are intang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in their own Devices.</p>
               <p>They have rewarded Evil unto themſelves.</p>
               <p>The Steps of their Strength are ſtraitned, their own Counſels have caſt them down.</p>
               <p>The Effects of their Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are heavy upon them.</p>
               <p>Is not their Condition heavier than their Complaint, and their Stroke heavier than their Groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings?</p>
               <p>O Lord our God their Sores are
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:33585:141"/>
not ſo great but thou canſt ſalve them.</p>
               <p>The Lord upholdeth all them that fall, and raiſeth up them who are bowed down.</p>
               <p>In regard that Sin hath been a means to bring them into Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, grant that Suffering may be a means to bring them out of Sin.</p>
               <p>Write their Sin legible in their Sorrows.</p>
               <p>Cauſe their Chaſtiſements to be remedies not ruins to them.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Arrows of Vengeance to wound the Old Man of Sin.</p>
               <p>Let the Rod beat out the Moths.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="233" facs="tcp:33585:141"/>
Cauſe the rough File to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Ruſt.</p>
               <p>Make the bitter Pills, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the peccant Humours.</p>
               <p>Let their be no worſe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of their Afflictions than the purging away their Iniquity and the taking away their Sin.</p>
               <p>That the Waters of Affliction may ſo ſeaſon their Earthen Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, that they may be freed from all tincture of Sin and Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>The more Correction the leſs Corruption we beſeech thee.</p>
               <p>If the Furnace be ſeven times hotter, cauſe it to make them ſeven times better.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="234" facs="tcp:33585:142"/>
In regard thou do'ſt bring them thro the Fire, refine them as Silver is refined, and try them as Gold is tryed.</p>
               <p>That they may learn Obedience by the things that they ſuffer.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the polliſhing of thoſe Stones to make them fit for the Building of the Temple.</p>
               <p>That their Chaſt'ning may yield unto them the peaceable Fruits of Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>Open their Ears to Diſcipline.</p>
               <p>That all the Black Lines of Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction may lead to the true Center of Happineſs.</p>
               <p>That thy Rods may become Sermons.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="235" facs="tcp:33585:142"/>
That they may hear the Rod and who hath appointed it.</p>
               <p>Put Wiſdom into their Inward Parts, and Undeſtanding into their Hearts.</p>
               <p>Add Inſtruction to Correction, that they may be corrigible by the Rod, leſt thou ſend thy Axe.</p>
               <p>That they may learn by Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, leſt thou bring them to Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>That they may be as Sea-marks unto them, that they in future beware of the dangerous Rocks that lie hid under the ſmooth Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Sin.</p>
               <p>Cauſe them to feel the weight of their Sin, as well as the weight of their Puniſhment.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="236" facs="tcp:33585:143"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake them to know their Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>on and their Sin, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be truly humbled, that thou, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>veſt put an end to all their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dies and turn away thine Anger and comfort them.</p>
               <p>Deliver them that are big with Grief.</p>
               <p>Tho they have lain among the Pots, that they may be as the Wings of a Dove cover'd with Silver, and his Feathers of Yellow Gold.</p>
               <p>Cauſe the Night of Sorrow to vaniſh by the appearance of the Sun of Mercy, like the Sun of Righteouſneſs with Healing in his Wings.</p>
               <p>That their Afflictions may be
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:33585:143"/>
Preparatives for future Bleſſings, and better Hearts to enjoy them.</p>
               <p>That thou may'ſt make them glad according to the days where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou haſt afflicted them, or the years wherein they have ſeen Evil.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt watehed over them to break them down, to root them out, and to deſtroy them; now watch over them to build and to plant.</p>
               <p>In the interim help them to take up their Contentment in they Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</p>
               <p>That they may ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to Gods <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If they cannot read Love in the Hands and Face of God, by reaſon
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:33585:144"/>
of Frowns and Strokes, teach them to draw by the Vail, and read Love in the Heart of God; and cry out the Thoughts of God are Thoughts of Love and Peace</p>
               <p>That they may truſt in the Name of the Lord, and ſtay upon their God.</p>
               <p>They 'ave loſt the Comforts which they could not keep, give them to keep the Comforts which they cannot loſe.</p>
               <p>In regard their Ciſterns are bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, lead them to the Fountain.</p>
               <p>Remember thy Footſtool in the day of thine Anger.</p>
               <p>Oh ſet bounds to thoſe Seas.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="239" facs="tcp:33585:144"/>
Don't always Chide, keep not thine Anger for ever.</p>
               <p>Don't triumph in farther Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions.</p>
               <p>Let thy Compaſſions ſay, It is enough.</p>
               <p>Plow not all the day to Sow.</p>
               <p>Their ſtrength is not as the ſtrength of Stones.</p>
               <p>Neither is their Fleſh of Braſs.</p>
               <p>Thou knoweſt their Frame, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member they are but Duſt.</p>
               <p>If thou ſhould'ſt be extream in marking what is done amiſs, who is able to abide thy Wrath.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="240" facs="tcp:33585:145"/>
Let it not be long before thou heal the Stroke of their Wound.</p>
               <p>Regard their Affliction when thou heareſt their Cry.</p>
               <p>Doth the Wild Aſs bray when he hath Graſs, or loweth the Oxe over his Fodder?</p>
               <p>Deep calleth unto Deep at the noiſe of thy Water-ſpouts, thy Waves and thy Billows are gone over them.</p>
               <p>Wilt thou break a Leaf driven with the Wind? Wilt thou pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the dry Stubble?</p>
               <p>Remember them in their low e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, for thy mercies endure for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="241" facs="tcp:33585:145"/>
Tho thou Chaſten them ſore, give thm not over unto Death.</p>
               <p>Tho thou take Vengeance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Inventions, yet forgive them: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99. 8.</p>
               <p>Be their Defence and Refuge in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he day of their Trouble, that they may ſing of thy Power.</p>
               <p>Give Power unto the Faint and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem that have no Might.</p>
               <p>Break the Yoke from their Neck, burſt their Bonds, command De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iverance for them.</p>
               <p>Let not the Needy always be forgotten, let not the Expectation of the Poor periſh for ever.</p>
               <p>Raiſe the Poor out of the Duſt,
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:33585:146"/>
and the Needy out of the Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill.</p>
               <p>Set them high from Affliction and make them Families like a Flock.</p>
               <p>Bring back their Souls from the Pit, and enlighten them with the Light of the Living.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="243" facs="tcp:33585:146"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>GRant that all thy Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to us may be a means to further us in that great Work; in making our Calling and Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure.</p>
               <p>That in this our day we may improve our Talents, get Oyl in our Lamps, Grace in our Hearts; that we may be own'd by the Bridegroom at his coming.</p>
               <p>Make us live Spiritually before we die Naturally.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="244" facs="tcp:33585:147"/>
That the Temple of Grace may be raiſed before the Tabernacle of Nature be taken down.</p>
               <p>That our Souls may be fit to be taken into Heaven, before our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies be fit to be put into the Earth.</p>
               <p>That the ſecond Birth may have place in us, leaſt the ſecond Death have power over us.</p>
               <p>Let our Prayers be as Incenſe and the Lifting up our Hands as an acceptable Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>Lord kindle our Sacrifice from Heaven.</p>
               <p>That our Prayers may be as a Key to unlock the Bowels of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="245" facs="tcp:33585:147"/>
Return Anſwers of Peaec into our own Boſoms.</p>
               <p>That the Trade we drive in Prayer may increaſe our Stock of Grace.</p>
               <p>We depend upon thee, for we of our ſelves can do nothing.</p>
               <p>Our Strength is never ſo un truſty, as when 'tis moſt truſted.</p>
               <p>Thou know'ſt what we have to do and ſuffer before our courſe be finiſhed.</p>
               <p>All Futurities are treaſured up in God.</p>
               <p>Thou knoweſt Sin hath cut the Lock where our Strength lay.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="246" facs="tcp:33585:148"/>
We have loſt the Rudder of Free Will.</p>
               <p>Oh whither will the turbulen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Waves of our Corrupt Affections carry us, if thou do not come to us and help us, and ſtay the rage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sea, and command <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Calm?</p>
               <p>If thy Preſence go along with us we ſhall have Reſt.</p>
               <p>Let thy everlaſting Arms be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us.</p>
               <p>Put thy Left Hand under our Head, and let thy Right Hand em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace us.</p>
               <p>If thou do'ſt not provide us a Pillar of a Cloud by Day, and a Pillar of Fire by Night: If thou
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:33585:148"/>
do'ſt not fight our Battles and make our Way plain before us, we ſhall never reach <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cover thou our Heads in a day of Battle, and teach our Hands to War and our Fingers to Fight.</p>
               <p>Our Souls have broke their Wings, thou only canſt reſtore us, therefore inable us that we may mount up with Wings as Eagles, that we may run and not be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that we may walk and not faint.</p>
               <p>If the Heavenly Bodies did not move, there would be no Motion here below.</p>
               <p>When thou didſt not lead <hi>Iſrael</hi> on they took up their Standings.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="248" facs="tcp:33585:149"/>
Inlarge our Steps under us, that our Feet do not ſlide.</p>
               <p>Gird us with Strength, for thou art our Rock, our Fortreſs, our Deliverer, the Strength in whom we will truſt, our Buckler, the Horn of our Salvation and high Tower.</p>
               <p>If the Face of the Sun be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, the Moon loſeth her Light; when thou hideſt thy Face we are in Darkneſs.</p>
               <p>Becauſe thou art our Strength we will wait upon thee, for God is our Defence.</p>
               <p>Unto thee our Strength will we ſing, for God is our Defence, the God of our Mercy.</p>
               <p>Stir up thy Strength and come and ſave us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="249" facs="tcp:33585:149"/>
That the Place of our Defence may be Munition of Rocks, that Bread may be given unto us, that our Waters may be ſure.</p>
               <p>Advance and confirm all our Reſolutions for doing Good, give a Prevailing Iſſue to all our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and cauſe Bleſſed Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to attend all our good Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes.</p>
               <p>If there be any good Deſires in us, thou haſt begun them; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them until the day of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Send Auxiliary Graces to actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the dull Habits of Inherent Graces.</p>
               <p>That the Buds of our Good De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires may bloſſom into Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:33585:150"/>
and that thoſe Bloſſoms may come to ſuch perfection as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Fruit of good Actions.</p>
               <p>That we may not only purpoſe to be religious, but religious to purpoſe.</p>
               <p>That we may not only deſire but endeavour, and give thou that bleſſing to our Endeavours, that they may be ſucceſsful, that we may do that which is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing unto thee.</p>
               <p>When we preſs forward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the high Price of our Calling, ſuffer not any diſcouragment to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten upon us.</p>
               <p>Suffer us not to unbend our Reſolutions for Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="251" facs="tcp:33585:150"/>
Suffer not the Earth to put out the Fire.</p>
               <p>Let not the things of the World choke our Zeal, nor ſtifle the Motions of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Tho all the Inſtruments ſound, ſuffer us not to fall down to the Image that <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> hath ſet up.</p>
               <p>Suffer not Secular Proviſo's to blunt the edge of our Zeal, nor the things of the World to eat out the Heart of Religion.</p>
               <p>Suffer not the Worlds Silver Trumpet to ſound a Retreat, to call us off from the Purſuit of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>Let not the Muſick of the World charm us aſleep.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="252" facs="tcp:33585:151"/>
Keep <hi>Satan</hi> from cuting the Sinews of our Endeavours.</p>
               <p>Suffer not the Darts of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation to pierce thro the Armour of our Reſolution.</p>
               <p>Suffer not our good Reſolutions to be vanquiſhed by the Impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of our baſe ſenſual Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Go thou along with us thro the Crowd of Oppoſition.</p>
               <p>Keep us from being worried with the power of Sin.</p>
               <p>Altho we cannot be kept alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether from falling, keep us from falling altogether.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="253" facs="tcp:33585:151"/>
Keep us from being carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any ways that ſhall diſhonour the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Hold us by the Right Hand, thou art the Lord our God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore encourage us and help us.</p>
               <p>Direct us in this Maze of Life and in the Buffle of the World.</p>
               <p>Let the Spirit of Truth guid us in all Truth.</p>
               <p>Give us a Safe Conduct thro all Caſualty, hide our lives with Chriſt in God.</p>
               <p>Keep us by thy Power thro Faith unto Salvation.</p>
               <p>In large our Hearts, that we may run in the Way of thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="254" facs="tcp:33585:152"/>
Suffer us not to truck our Faith for our Liberty.</p>
               <p>Confirm us unto the end, that we may be blameleſs in the Day of our Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>In regard our Impatient and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate Deſires after Carnal Pleaſures always return laden with an Intolerable Burthen of Grief and Sorrow, and that Sin loſeth what Repentance gains, therefore Caution us.</p>
               <p>Put thy Fear in our Hearts, that we may not depart from thy Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</p>
               <p>Sins Gilded Pills are the Fore-runners of Bitter Potions, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore work in us a diſlike of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="255" facs="tcp:33585:152"/>
Keep us from catching at the Bait of Pleaſure, leſt we hang up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Hook of perpetual Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Order our Steps, and uphold us with thy Free Spirit.</p>
               <p>Cauſe Faith and Fear to go hand in hand, that Faith may keep us chearful, and that Fear may keep us ſerious; that Faith may keep us from ſinking in Deſpair, and that Fear may keep us from floating in Preſumption.</p>
               <p>Why ſhould we deſpair, God can help us? Why ſhould we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, God can croſs us?</p>
               <p>That a holy Alacrity may be temper'd with a gracious Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="256" facs="tcp:33585:153"/>
Keep our Feet from falling, that we may walk before thee in the Light of the Living.</p>
               <p>Let us hear the Still Voice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind us, when we turn to the Right hand or the Left.</p>
               <p>The Lord is our Shepherd.</p>
               <p>The Shepherd when he ſees his Sheep ſtraying out of their Bounds, he calls out unto them.</p>
               <p>Our Shepherd is the Living Lord, who is acquainted with all our Ways, and pondereth all our Goings.</p>
               <p>When thou O Lord feeſt us Wandering out of our Goſpel Rules, lift up thy Voice; either the voice of thy Word or the voice
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:33585:153"/>
of thy Meſſengers, or the Voice of our Conſciences; or the Voice of thy Spirit: That we may return to the green paſtures and to the ſtill waters.</p>
               <p>Give Light unto our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, Order in our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Pliableneſs in our Will, that we may be exemplary in our Lives.</p>
               <p>Deliver us not onely from the Sins of the Times; but from the Times of Sin.</p>
               <p>That we may be found always moving in the Orb of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>Make us ſo Honourable as to be born of thee, ſo Wiſe as to know thee, ſo Beautiful that we
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:33585:154"/>
may bear thy Image, ſo Rich as to be rich in Faith, ſo Victorious as to overcome the World, ſo happy as to enjoy thy ſelf, ſo bleſſed with peace as to have the peace of God, which paſſeth all underſtanding; then we ſhall be ſure of true joy, the joy of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Work our Names in the Frame of thine own Glory.</p>
               <p>Make us bleſſed in this Life, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in Death, and glorious after Death.</p>
               <p>Make out unto us that thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is ours to pardon us, that thy Blood is ours to cleanſe us, thy Merits ours to juſtifie us, thy Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ours to cloath us, thy Spirit ours to lead us, thy Grace ours to inrich us, and thy Glory ours to crown us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="259" facs="tcp:33585:154"/>
Make us Maſters of ſo much Conſideration, that we are ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming down the Stream of Time, and it will not belong before we lanch into the Ocean of Eternity.</p>
               <p>Teach us ſo to number our days, that we may apply our hearts unto Wiſdom.</p>
               <p>That we may live in thy fear and die in thy favour, reſt in thy peace, ariſe by thy power, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in thy glory for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>This and whatſoever elſe we ſhould ask for our ſelves or any other, let it be granted unto us and to them, upon the alone ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our great Lord and ever bleſſed Redeemer, who was given for us, who was made a Curſe for
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:33585:155"/>
us, who inexpreſſibly ſuffer'd for us, who ſatisfied Divine Juſtice for us, who was made reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for us, who died and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for us: Who prepared glory for us, and ever maketh Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for us. For him we give all praiſes, in him we ever deſire to be found, rendering unto the moſt glorious Majeſty of Heaven, as we for ever will acknowledge moſt due, all Honour, Glory, Power, Might, Reverence, Fear, and Obedience, World without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="261" facs="tcp:33585:155"/>
               <head>The Bleſsing with which the Author uſed to diſmiſs his Congregation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Almighty Power of God the Father</hi> vanquiſh and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome whatſoever may hinder you from him, and give you ſtrength to do his acceptable Will in all things: <hi>The moſt Bright Wiſdom of God the Son</hi> inlighten you and lead you to all things which may bring you forward to him. <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpeakable and Super-abounding Love of God the Holy</hi>
                  <pb n="262" facs="tcp:33585:156"/>
                  <hi>Ghoſt</hi> pierce thro all the Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in you, kindle and unite your love to him with a moſt ardent and pleaſing turning, all your Powers and Strength, that you may follow his ſweet Calling and moſt amorous drawing: <hi>Whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the more than Moſt Glorious Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> hath called you: Namely, From the Love of this Deceitful World to the Injoyment of God and his Riches, and Unſpeakable Bleſſedneſs; ſo that by Grace you may be that which you are not nor can be by Nature. To whom be all Honour, Praiſe, Obedience, and Reverence. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33585:156"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
